<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The benefite of affliction. A sermon, first preached, and afterwards enlarged, by Charles Richardson preacher at Saint Katharines neare to the Tower of London</title>
            <author>Richardson, Charles, fl. 1612-1617.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 133 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 57 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10734</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21013</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119812</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855018</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855018</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20488</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10734)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20488)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1556:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The benefite of affliction. A sermon, first preached, and afterwards enlarged, by Charles Richardson preacher at Saint Katharines neare to the Tower of London</title>
                  <author>Richardson, Charles, fl. 1612-1617.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 96 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Lionell Snowdon for William Butlar, and are to be sold at his shop in the Bulwarke, neare the Tower of London,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20488:1"/>
            <p>THE BENEFITE <hi>of Affliction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Sermon, firſt preached, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards enlarged, by <hi>Charles Richardſon</hi> Preacher at <hi>Saint Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tharines</hi> neare to the Tower of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 94.12.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Bleſſed is the man whom thou cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſeſt, O Lord, and teacheſt him in thy Lawe.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>Lionell Snowdon,</hi> for <hi>W. But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in the Bulwarke, neare the Tower of London. 1616.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20488:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20488:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>¶ To the right honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable</hi> and truly Religious Lady, <hi>the Lady ELIZABETH</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſe of Lincolne, grace and <hi>peace be mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Firſt preched this Sermon at the buriall of one,<note place="margin">M. Brockleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by a Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmith in Cheapſide.</note> who on his death<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed gaue or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that this Text might then bee handled. And hauing ſince, vpon ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther occaſion, enlarged the ſame, I haue preſumed, in your Honors
<pb facs="tcp:20488:3"/>
name, to make it more publike, by committing it to the Preſſe. The reaſon that mooued mee, beſides mine owne priuate reſpect (wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I confeſſe I am bound to doe your Honour all the ſeruice I can, in regarde of the great fauour which for many yeares I haue found at your hands) is this, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I know the Doctrine of it doeth moſt properly appertaine vnto you: who a long time haue felt theſe bleſſed fruits of afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your ſelfe in a moſt plentifull manner.<note place="margin">Iames 1.4. Rom. 8.37.</note> If euer <hi>Patience</hi> hath had <hi>her perfect worke</hi> in anie, it hath beene in you: who haue not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie been thereby <hi>more then a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour:</hi> but alſo haue learned to contemne and deſpiſe all outward croſſes, as not able to come neare your ſoule, beeing mounted vp ſo high aboue their reach. Yea
<pb facs="tcp:20488:3"/>
hereby the graces which GOD hath wrought in your Honour, haue beene ſo tried, like golde in the furnace, as they haue ſhined forth, in ſuch excellent and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous manner, that all that haue knowne you, haue beene drawne into admiration thereof. For mine owne part, I muſt needes acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that I neuer came to your Honour, but I went away aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, to ſee my ſelfe ſo much infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour in grace vnto you. I haue many times wondred, to beholde your exceeding diligent attention in hearing the word, your bleſſed memorie to retaine the thinges which you haue heard, and your godlie care to make an holie vſe thereof in the whole courſe of your life. And as your deſire is great to heare the word in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique: ſo you ſpend much time in
<pb facs="tcp:20488:4"/>
the priuat reading of the ſame, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it your chief delight,<note place="margin">Pſal: 1.2. 1 Cor. 1.5. Heb. 5.14.</note> 
               <hi>to medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate in the Lawe of the Lord day and night:</hi> whereby you are made <hi>rich in knowledge:</hi> and, <hi>through long cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome haue your witte exerciſed, to diſcerne both good and euill.</hi> But you haue not thought it ſufficient to bee thus Chriſtianly affected your ſelfe, but your care hath bin likewiſe extended to your chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren that they alſo might be trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vp in ſound religion. It would do a man good, to heare the ſweet leſſons and gracious inſtructions, which you like another <hi>Bath-ſheba</hi> haue taught your little ones,<note place="margin">Prou. 31.1.</note> cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them as yong <hi>Timotheus</hi> did, to know the holy Scriptures,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.15.</note> euen from their cradles. Whereby you haue made ſo deepe an impreſſion of godlineſſe in their hearts, as (I truſt) the diuell ſhall neuer be able
<pb facs="tcp:20488:4"/>
to raſe out. Neither hath your goodnes bin dammed vp in your owne priuate familie, but it hath alſo flowed foorth to the good of others. For at ſuch time as God denied your Honour that plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vſe of his word, which I know you thirſted and panted after, as earneſtlie as euer did the Hart <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the riuers of water,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 24.1.</note> whenſoeuer you had anie oportunitie of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it offered vnto you, you did not ingroſſe it, as worldlings doe their commodities, to your owne priuate vſe alone, but with good <hi>Cornelius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 10.24.</note> you called together your neighbours and friends, that they alſo might bee partakers of the grace of God with you. And howſoeuer you haue not in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times had ſuch means to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme externall works of charitie, as God hath afforded vnto others:
<pb facs="tcp:20488:5"/>
yet to your power,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 8.3.</note> yea and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond your power, you haue been willing to do good that way alſo. For you ſpent not your eſtate in pride and brauerie (for that you neuer affected) but your richeſt dreſſings and attire were the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments of the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> as <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> ſaith. Your earings were the word of God, your neck-laces the yoke of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> your ſilken and veluet garments were pietie and holineſſe. By which meanes you ſpared much from vaine and idle expences (wherein too many of your place doe greatly exceede) that you might haue ſomething, to giue to ſuch as ſtand need of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe: eſpecially to the Miniſters of the word, which brought vnto you the glad tidings of peace and ſaluation. There is none that hath beene more readie to entertaine
<pb facs="tcp:20488:5"/>
them at all times, nor to vſe them with greater reſpect then your Honour hath done. And as I can witneſſe, how earneſtlie you haue deſired, that you might but liue to doe more good in the Church of God: ſo I doubt not, but God hauing at the laſt, in mercie gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted your deſire,<note place="margin">Pſa. 66.13, 14</note> you will be mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to pay the vowes, <hi>which your lips haue promiſed, and your mouth hath ſpoken in your affliction.</hi> I doubt not, but with vertuous <hi>Ruth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ruth 3.10.</note> you will <hi>ſhew more goodneſſe in the latter end, then at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning:</hi> that as all that haue knowne you, haue hitherto called you, <hi>The good Lady Clinton,</hi> ſo you may now be called, <hi>The good Counteſse of Lincolne.</hi> You ſee (right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable) how farre I haue been tranſported with the admiration of your excellent vertues. God is
<pb facs="tcp:20488:6"/>
my witneſſe, I haue not done it to flatter, or <hi>to giue Titles</hi> to your Honour, for then <hi>my Maker would reprooue me:</hi> and I know your hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie is ſuch, as you loue not to heare your owne praiſes. But I do it in the ſinceritie of my ſoule, that GOD may haue the glorie of his graces, and that the Church may be edified by your example: I would all the great Ladies in the Land would treade in your ſteps: ſo ſhould they ſhine as ſo many glorious diamonds in the Church of God. For it is not the greatnes of their birth, nor the eminence of their places, that can ſo enno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble them, and make them ſo tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie honourable in the ſight of God and his children, as the admirable graces which appeare in you. I pray GOD, euen from the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of my heart, to bleſſe your
<pb facs="tcp:20488:6"/>
Honour with many happie daies, in this life, to perfect the good worke which hee hath begunne in you, and in the end, to bring you to that immortall inheritance that fadeth not away, which is reſerued in Heauen for you.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours most humbly deuoted, <hi>CHARLES RICHARDSON.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20488:7"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the godly, vertuous</hi> and religious Ladies, the <hi>Ladie Katharine Scot, the</hi> Lady <hi>Iſabel Bowes,</hi> the Lady <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces S. Paul,</hi> and the Ladie <hi>Frances Wray, increaſe of grace</hi> and fruition of <hi>glory.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy Ladies:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S God hath v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited you all in the bondes of nature and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance; ſo I am bolde to ioyne you all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of this Sermon. I confeſſe, in it ſelfe, it is not worthy the acceptance of any one of you. But ſeeing it hath pleaſed God, to make you all inſtruments of much good and comfort vnto mee, and I know not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:20488:7"/>
I ſhall euer haue opportunity, to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh ſeuerall things in euery one of your names in particular: I haue thought good, to take this occaſion, to manifeſt my thankefull acknowledgement of the kindeneſſe of you all in generall: which hath beene extended, not to me onely, but to many others of my calling. For I may truly giue this teſtimony of you, that you haue all ſhewed great loue to the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Miniſters of God, and when any of them haue reſorted vnto you, you haue according to the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> precept,<note place="margin">Phil 2.29.</note> 
               <hi>recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued them with all gladneſſe, and made much of them.</hi> The matter of this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon is concerning affliction, whereof you haue all had your portion more or leſſe: and therefore, the Doctrine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in it, doth fitly appertaine to you all. But eſpecially to you my good Ladie <hi>Scot,</hi> whom the Lord hath cauſed to drinke deeper of this cuppe then many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. But as it hath pleaſed God, hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to to ſupport you with grace and patience: ſo I doubt not, but hee will, in his good time, make a bleſſed end with you, as hee did with <hi>Iob,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iames 5.11. Pſal. 90.15.</note> making you <hi>glad againe
<pb facs="tcp:20488:8"/>
according to the yeares wherein you haue ſeene euill.</hi> If theſe meditatations of mine may miniſter any comfort vnto you, or to any other in the like caſe, I ſhal thinke my labour well beſtowed. And thus preſuming that you will kindely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of this my poore ſeruice, which in my ſincereſt affection I tender vnto you, <hi>I commend all your Ladiſhips to God, and to the word of his grace, who is able to build you further, and to giue you an inheritance among them that are ſanctified.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Ladiſhips in all due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull affection. CHARLES RICHARDSON,</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:20488:8"/>
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Pag. 7. li. 4. reade, diuers tentations. pag. 9. li. 17. reade, borne. pag. 10. li. 18. reade ſiluer. lin. 26. reade, army. pag 11 li. 4 reade, were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained pa. 28. li. 10. reade, concerning inward tentations, is true alſo of outward affli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tions. pa 35. li. 10. reade, ſtrange. pa. 40. li. 5. put out And. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a. 41. li. 18. reade, broken in pag 45. li. 6. for violent, reade, godly. ibid in marg. lege ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacia.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:20488:9"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:20488:9"/>
            <head>THE BENEFITE <hi>of Affliction.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſal. 119.71.</hi>
                  </bibl> It is good for mee that I haue beene Afflicted, that I may learne thy Statutes.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F it bee lawfull to make compariſons betweene one part of the holy Scripture and another,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119, 129 2. Tim. 3.16:</note> which is all moſt <hi>excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent,</hi> as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, being <hi>inſpired</hi> by one and the ſame bleſſed ſpirit of God: wee may truely ſay that there is no part more worthy then the booke of <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> and in them, none more full of heauenly inſtruction then this <hi>Pſalme.</hi> The author whereof is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally agreed vpon to be <hi>Dauid,</hi> whome
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:20488:10"/>
the Scripture hath ſtiled, <hi>The ſweete ſinger of Iſrael.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2, Sam, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3, 1.</note> Who as he had a good facultie in the art of diuine <hi>Poetry,</hi> &amp; a great dexteritie in penning of <hi>Pſalms,</hi> to the glory of God, and the edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Church: ſo it is euident that he ſhewed the excellencie of his ſkill in compoſing this <hi>Pſalme:</hi> being there vnto occaſioned and excited by the great afflictions that were vpon him. For the <hi>Pſalme</hi> ſeemeth to haue beene penned in the time of his exile and ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, whereby hee laboureth to confirme his faith, by many comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table meditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the word of God. The matter of the <hi>Pſalme</hi> containeth many inſtructions and prayers, all ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to direct vs in the way of godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. The generall propoſition of it is this, that they that are truely godly, are truely bleſſed, and that they are truely godly, that are acquainted with the word of God, and are carefull to frame their liues according to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections and rules thereof.</p>
            <p>And therefore he laboureth by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny arguments throughout the whole
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:20488:10"/>
               <hi>Pſalme,</hi> and eſpecially by his owne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to ſtirre vp all the children of God, both to the continuall medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and due practiſe of the word.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Pſalme,</hi> as it is the longeſt of all the reſt, being diuided into two and twentie ſeuerall parts: ſo it is more cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly and more artificially penned then any of the reſt. For firſt, all the parts and diuiſions of it are of equall length, each of them conſiſting of eight verſes. Againe, euery diuiſion in the originall beginneth with an <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew</hi> letter according to the <hi>Alphabet,</hi> and euery verſe in that diuiſion begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth with the ſame letter. And laſt of all,<note place="margin">Verſe 122:</note> there is not any verſe in the whole <hi>Pſalme</hi> but one, which maketh not ſome mention of the word of God, and hath not ſome title or other, to ſet out and commend the excellencie of it. As it is called the <hi>Lawe,</hi> the <hi>Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies,</hi> the <hi>Waies,</hi> the <hi>Precepts,</hi> the <hi>Statutes,</hi> the <hi>Commaundements,</hi> the <hi>Iudgements,</hi> the <hi>promiſe,</hi> the <hi>truth,</hi> the <hi>ordinances,</hi> the <hi>name of God &amp;c.</hi> Now the reaſons why the <hi>Prophet</hi> is ſo
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:20488:11"/>
exquiſite in framing of this <hi>Pſalme,</hi> is to commend the excellencie of the matter contained in it, that ſo wee may be ſtirred vp to regard it with greater attention. For where the Lord is cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in ſpeaking, there ſhould we be moſt diligent in hearing and learning. As alſo it was no ſmall helpe to the memory: for being written in the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew</hi> tongue, it was to the <hi>Iewes</hi> in ſteed of an holy <hi>Alphabet,</hi> which they might learne as our children doe the <hi>A.B.C.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now concerning this ninth part of the <hi>Pſalme,</hi> wherein this verſe that I haue read is contained, the <hi>Prophet</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing firſt thankfully acknowledged Gods mercie in <hi>dealing gratiouſly with him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ve ſ. 65.</note> he maketh his petition to be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther taught &amp; inſtructed in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Gods will.<note place="margin">Verſ. 66.</note> Which petition he vrgeth and inforceth with diuerſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. Firſt, becauſe hee had <hi>beleeued Gods Commaundement</hi> in the end of that verſe. A ſecond reaſon is taken from his former vntowardneſſe and vntractableneſſe, that hee had beene
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:20488:11"/>
like an vnruly beaſt,<note place="margin">Verſ. 67.</note> that would not keep the way without beating. Where by the way, hee ſheweth the benefite that the children of God doe receiue by the croſſe. Namely, that it ſubdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the vntamedneſſe of their nature, and maketh them liue in better order. After this he repeateth his former ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement of Gods goodneſſe,<note place="margin">Verſ. 68.</note> and renueth his petition to be taught, backing it with another reaſon in the two next verſes. And in this verſe hee repeateth that which hee ſaid before concerning affliction, though in other words. <hi>It is good for mee that I haue beene afflicted, that I may learne thy Statutes.</hi> Wherein wee are to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, firſt, the perſon that was afflicted, and that is <hi>Dauid</hi> himſelfe. <hi>It is good for me, that I haue beene afflicted.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, the fruite which hee found in his affliction, which is propounded firſt generally, <hi>It is good for mee, &amp;c.</hi> And then by a particular effect, which was wrought in him thereby, <hi>That I may learne thy Statutes.</hi> And thus we ſee the coherence that theſe words
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:20488:12"/>
haue with the former, together with the ſum and reſolution of them. Let vs now come to the ſeuerall inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons contained in them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is good for me.)</hi> In the example of <hi>Dauid,</hi> we learne, that euen the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly themſelues are ſubiect to many af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions. The deareſt of Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren may, and oftentimes doe ſuffer affliction with varietie,<note place="margin">Pſal. 34, 19</note> extremitie, and continuance. <hi>Many</hi> ſaith <hi>Dauid, or great, are the troubles of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 80, 5.</note> Yea God doth many times feede his owne children <hi>with the bread of teares, and giueth them teares to drinke in great meaſure.</hi> And hee threatneth euen thoſe, with whom he hath made a ſure couenant, and from whom hee will neuer take his mercie and louing kindneſſe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 89, 30, 31, 32.33.</note> that <hi>if they forſake his lawe and walke not in his iudgements: If they breake his ſtatutes and keepe not his commaundements, hee will viſit their tranſgreſſion with the rod, and their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquitie with ſtrokes.</hi> And to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe is that ſaying of <hi>Solomon,</hi> that euen <hi>a iuſt man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro 24, 16</note> 
               <hi>falleth ſeuen times,</hi> that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:20488:12"/>
is, is afflicted oft and many times. And the <hi>Apoſtle Iames</hi> exhorteth the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,<note place="margin">Iam. 1, 2,</note> to <hi>count it exceeding ioy when they fall into tentations,</hi> or afflictions. And hereof the <hi>Prophet Dauid</hi> himſelfe is a moſt pregnant example. Hee was <hi>a man that God had ſet vp on high,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 23, 1,</note> 
               <hi>the Annointed of the God of Iacob.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 13.14.</note> Yea by the Lords owne teſtimony, he was <hi>a man after his owne heart:</hi> and yet he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth of himſelfe, that <hi>daily hee had beene puniſhed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 73, 14:</note> 
               <hi>and chaſtened euery mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</hi> Euery day that we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ouer his head, brough with it ſome affliction or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. He was perſecuted by <hi>Saul,</hi> who purſued him from place to place,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 26:20</note> 
               <hi>as one would hunt a partridge in the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines.</hi>
               <note place="margin">and 22, 9, and 23, 19, 20</note> He was falſely accuſed by <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eg,</hi> that curſed <hi>Edomite,</hi> betrayed and diſcouered by the falſe hearted <hi>Zi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phims.</hi> He was diſcomforted and deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by his wife that lay in his boſom. He had many heartbreakings with his children. <hi>Ziglag,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 30:1, 5.</note> the towne which <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſh</hi> king of <hi>Gath</hi> had giuen him for his habitation, was ſacked &amp; burnt by the <hi>Amalekites,</hi> &amp; his wiues y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:20488:13"/>
comfort of his life, were taken priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. Yea it may appeare to all that ſhall read his ſtory in both the bookes of <hi>Samuel,</hi> that, as if hee had beene a man borne to miſery, hee ſcarce had one good day in all his life.</p>
            <p>Neit er was this the caſe of <hi>Dauid</hi> alone, but euen all the children of God mentioned in the Scripture, haue alſo beene partakers of the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.<note place="margin">Rom. 9.13.</note> 
               <hi>Iacob</hi> that holy <hi>Patriarke,</hi> on whom God had ſet his loue before he was borne, was many waies afflicted in the greateſt part of his life. He was hated of his brother, and for feare of his fury, forced to leaue his owne cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try and his fathers houſe, and to liue as a ſeruant in a ſtrange land for the ſpace of twentie yeares.<note place="margin">Gen. 31.41.</note> He was vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the vnkindneſſe of his churliſh Vncle, who notwithſtanding his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſeruice, changed his wages ten times. He was vpbraided and ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by his Coſins, the ſonnes of <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban.</hi> He was grieued with the peeuiſh behauiour of his wiues, and much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comforted by his children. <hi>Iob</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:20488:13"/>
though a godly man, one of whom the Lord himſelfe teſtified, that he was <hi>an vpright and a iuſt man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 1.8.</note> 
               <hi>one that feared God and eſchewed euill:</hi> Yet his life for a long time, was euen a Mappe of miſery. It was no ſmall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction to looſe ſuch a deale of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance all in a day, to haue his children ſo pittifully diſmembred, to haue his wife and his friends that ſhould haue aſſwaged his ſorrow,<note place="margin">Iob. 16.2. and 6.4.</note> to play the <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable comforters,</hi> and to adde afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vnto his miſery, and which was worſt of all, to haue <hi>the terrours of God to fight againſt him. Solomon</hi> alſo, of whom the Lord ſaid before euer hee were bone; <hi>He ſhall bee my Sonne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Chr. 22:10</note> 
               <hi>and I will bee his Father,</hi> and concerning whom he promiſed, that <hi>his mercie ſhould neuer depart from him as he tooke it from Saul:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 7.15.</note> though he enioyed great proſperitie for many yeares: yet when <hi>he turned his he art from the Lord God of Iſraell &amp; keept not that which he had commaunded him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. King. 11 9.10.</note> the Lord raiſed him vp aduerſa ies one after another, which moleſted him with warres al the dayes
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:20488:14"/>
of his life.<note place="margin">1. Kin. 11, 14 23.26</note> As firſt <hi>Hadad,</hi> then <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon,</hi> and after him <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> and when he was dead, ten tribes of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome were rent away from his ſonne. And <hi>Hezekiah</hi> a man ſo <hi>vpright in the ſight of the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Kin. 18, 5, 5</note> 
               <hi>as after him there was none like him among all the Kings of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah, neither were there any ſuch before him;</hi> was notwithſtanding exerciſed with grieuous and continuall afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.<note place="margin">Verſe 13, 14, 15, 16</note> Firſt of all, <hi>Sanecherib</hi> king of <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyria</hi> came vp <hi>againſt all the ſtrong ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Iudah, and tooke them:</hi> and hee to make his peace, was conſtrained to giue him <hi>three hundreth talents of ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and thirtie talents of gold.</hi> For rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of which ſumme, hee was forced to take all the ſiluer, that was found in the houſe of the Lord, and in the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the kings houſe, yea he pulled off the plates of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doore of the temple, and the pillars which himſelfe had co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered ouer, and gaue them to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vp of the tribute. And yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all this,<note place="margin">17.</note> 
               <hi>Sanecherib</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after ſent a great arny againſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem to deſtroy it,<note place="margin">and 19, 10, 11.</note> and cauſed <hi>Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhakeh</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:20488:14"/>
with a blacke mouth, to the breaking of <hi>Hezekiahs</hi> heart, to blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme the name of the liuing God. And he was no ſooner by Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie deliuered out of this danger,<note place="margin">and 20, 1,</note> but ſtraightway he was viſited with a ſore ſickneſſe (and as ſome thinke with the plague) which in all appearance was vnto death. So <hi>Lazarus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk 16.20, 21 22</note> at whoſe death the <hi>Angels</hi> of heauen were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed to carry his ſoule into <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams boſome,</hi> was in his lifetime poore, impotent, harbourleſſe, diſtreſſed, and vnpittied. In a word, theſe famous <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies</hi> of the world, that the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſpeaketh off, <hi>of whom the world was not worthy, were tryed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11, 36.37.38.</note> 
               <hi>ſome by mockings and ſcourgings, ſome by bonds and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment. They were ſtoned, they were hewen aſunder, they were tempted, they were ſlaine by the ſword, they wandered vp and downe in ſheepes ſkins &amp; goates ſkins, being deſtitut, afflicted &amp; tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi> And as this is true in the generall, that Gods children are ſubiect to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny &amp; great afflictions: ſo it is true alſo in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> particuler, that there is not any ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:20488:15"/>
kinde of calamitie, but it may befall a godly man. There can be no greater griefe to godly parents, then to be troubled with wicked &amp; grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe children: and yet the Scripture hath many examples, of the holieſt men that euer liued, that haue beene afflicted that way.<note place="margin">Gen. 6.9 and 9.22.25.</note> 
               <hi>Noah</hi> was <hi>a iuſt and vpright man in his time, and wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with God:</hi> yet had he a wretched <hi>Cham</hi> that ſcoffed at the infirmities of his father, and therefore was curſed, both himſelfe, and his poſteritie. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> that was <hi>the Father of all them that beleeue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 4.11.</note> had a wicked <hi>Iſhmael, the ſonne of the bondwoman,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 21.9.</note> who, by mocks and taunts,<note place="margin">Gal. 4.29.</note> 
               <hi>perſecuted Iſaack the ſonne of the promiſe.</hi> Holy <hi>Iſaak</hi> had a <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane Eſau</hi> as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> calleth him,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.16.</note> who of ſet purpoſe to diſpleaſe his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tooke him wiues of other nations,<note place="margin">Gen. 26.34.35. and 27.46 and 28.8 9.</note> as bad as himſelfe, who by their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience and rebellion, were <hi>a griefe of minde</hi> to his parents, and made his mother <hi>wearie of her life.</hi> Good <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> was troubled with <hi>Simeon and Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ui, brethren in euill,</hi> who <hi>in their wrath
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:20488:15"/>
and ſelfe will,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 34.30. and 49, 5, 6</note> committed ſuch a bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die outrage vpon the <hi>Sichemites,</hi> as cauſed their father <hi>to bee abhorred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the inhabitants of the Land. Eli</hi> the <hi>Prieſt,</hi> a good man, had ſonnes that were <hi>wicked and knewe not the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 2.12.17, 22.</note> who behaued themſelues ſo vile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in their places, <hi>lying with the women that aſſembled at the doore of the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle of the congregation, that men ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred the offering of the Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">and 3.20.</note> 
               <hi>Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Samuel, the Lords Prophet,</hi> as hee is called by the holy Ghoſt, had ſonnes that <hi>walked not in his wayes, but turned aſide after lucre,</hi>
               <note place="margin">and 8.3.</note> 
               <hi>and tooke rewards and peruerted iudgement.</hi> And <hi>Dauid</hi> of whom wee haue heard ſuch high co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation before, had as much heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breake by his children, as euer poore father could haue. Firſt <hi>Amnon</hi> moſt beaſtly rauiſhed and defloured <hi>Tamar</hi> his owne ſiſter. Afterward <hi>Abſalom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 13.14.24.28.</note> to reuenge that villeny, inuited him to a feaſt at his Sheepeſheering, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his ſeruants treacherouſly to kill him. And in the end hee rebelled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his father,<note place="margin">cap. 15.16.17, 18</note> driue him out of his
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:20488:16"/>
kingdom, and had not God preuented him, would haue taken the Crowne from his head. It is no ſmall miſerie, to be expoſed to open contempt and reproach in the world, to be deſpiſed and made the laughing ſtocke of baſe people. And yet this was <hi>Iobs</hi> caſe, and that in as high a degree as poſſibly could be. For ſo he complaineth, that euen they <hi>whoſe fathers hee refuſed to ſet with the dogs of his flocke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 31.1.</note> mocked him and inſulted ouer him. Yea <hi>the children of villaines,</hi>
               <note place="margin">8 9.10.</note> and ſuch as <hi>were more vile then the earth,</hi> made him their <hi>ſong</hi> and their <hi>talke.</hi> Yea they <hi>did not ſpare to ſpit in his face.</hi> Neither was this indignitie offered him by ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers onely, but he was diſpiſed alſo in his owne family.<note place="margin">and 19.15,</note> 
               <hi>They that dwelt in his houſe</hi> (as he ſaith) <hi>and his maides tooke him for a ſtranger.</hi>
               <note place="margin">16</note> 
               <hi>He called his ſeruant but he would not anſwere, though he pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him with his mouth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">17.</note> Yea <hi>his breath was ſtrange to his wife, though he prayed her for the childrens ſake of his owne bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</hi> Hee that ſhall conſider the great authoritie that <hi>Iob</hi> was in before the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:20488:16"/>
Lord humbled him, as hee ſaith, how men of all ſorts eſteemed and reueren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced him, may eaſily thinke, what a griefe it was to his heart, to bee now made a laughing ſtocke to fooles. And <hi>Dauid,</hi> had his part likewiſe in the ſame croſſe.<note place="margin">Pſal. 35 15, 16</note> For <hi>the abiects aſſembled themſelues againſt him,</hi> in time of his aduerſitie, <hi>they tare him and ceaſed not. The ſcoffers at bankets gnaſhed their teeth againſt him.</hi> Yea,<note place="margin">and 69.11.12</note> 
               <hi>he became a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe and a byword vnto them,</hi> and <hi>the very drunkards made ſongs of him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a grieuous thing to bee impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned,<note place="margin">and 107, 10.</note> to <hi>lye in darkeneſſe in the ſhadowe of death, faſt bound in mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery and yron,</hi> as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith. And yet many of Gods deareſt children haue bin tryed and afflicted therwith. <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> a good man, and one that was alwayes carefull not to ſinne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God,<note place="margin">Gen. 39.19.20.</note> by the falſe accuſation of his <hi>Miſtreſſe</hi> was put in priſon, where hee lay diuerſe yeeres, ſo as his <hi>feete was hurt in the ſtockes and the yron entred into his ſoule.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 105:18,</note>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:20488:17"/>
               <hi>Ieremiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 1.5</note> a man that was <hi>ſanctified by the Lord before hee came out of the wombe, and ordeined to be a Prophet,</hi> was often brought into this affliction. Firſt,<note place="margin">and 20, 1, 2,</note> 
               <hi>Paſhur the Prieſt ſmote him, and put him in the ſtockes that were in the gate of Beniamin.</hi>
               <note place="margin">and 32, 2,</note> After this, <hi>hee was ſhut vp in the court of the priſon, that was in the King of Iudahs houſe.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>the princes ſmote him, and laide him in priſon in the houſe of Iehonathan the ſcribe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">and 37.15, 16,</note> 
               <hi>where hee remained in the dungeon a long time.</hi>
               <note place="margin">and 38, 6,</note> And laſt of all, <hi>they tooke him &amp; caſt him into the dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon that was in the court of the priſon, and let him downe with cordes, where there was no water but mire: ſo that he ſtacke faſt in the mire.</hi> So likewiſe <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaiah</hi> a faithfull <hi>Prophet,</hi> by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement of <hi>Ahab,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kin, 22, 27,</note> was put into the priſon houſe, where <hi>he was fed with the bread of affliction, and with water of affliction.</hi> And the <hi>Apoſtle Peter</hi> was caught vp by <hi>Herod,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 12, 4, 6, 7</note> 
               <hi>and put in priſon, and deliuered to foure quaternions of ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers to be kept,</hi> where hee was <hi>bound with two chaines,</hi> not his feete onely,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:20488:17"/>
but his hands alſo. And the <hi>Apoſtle Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> were deliuered to a cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell <hi>Iaylor,</hi>
               <note place="margin">and 16.23.24</note> who <hi>caſt them into the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome,</hi> or dungeon <hi>of the priſon, and made faſt their feete in the ſtockes.</hi> And thus were many of Gods bleſſed <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs</hi> vſed in the time of <hi>Popery.</hi> Who were not onely put in priſon, but they were kept in the ſtockes both hands and feete, ſo long, as ſome of them dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as they ſate.</p>
            <p>Shipwrake is a fearefull thing and a heauie affliction: yet the <hi>Apoſtle Paul</hi> ſuffered it <hi>thriſe,</hi> as he ſaith himſelfe.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 11.25.</note> The <hi>Euangeliſt S. Luke</hi> recordeth one of them at large. Namely, that they were <hi>toſted with an exceeding tempeſt,</hi> in ſo much as they were enforced to <hi>ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the ſhip,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 27.18.19 20.</note> by caſting the goods into the ſea, yea <hi>with their owne hands to caſt out the tackling of the ſhip.</hi> Yea the tempeſt that lay vpon them was of that continuance, that <hi>neither ſunne nor ſtarres for many dayes appeared, and all hope that they ſhould be ſaued was taken away.</hi> And in the end,<note place="margin">41.43.44.</note> 
               <hi>the forepart</hi> of the ſhip <hi>ſtacke faſt in a narrow place of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:20488:18"/>
the ſea, and could not be moued,</hi> and the hinder part was broken with the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of the waues. And the men that were in her, conſtrained ſo many as could ſwimme, to caſt themſelues into the ſea, and ſo goe out to land, and the reſt, ſome vpon bords, and ſome on pieces of the ſhip, to eſcape and ſaue themſelues. He that had ſtood on the ſhore at that time, no doubt ſhould haue ſeene a fearefull and lamentable ſpectacle: but hee that had beene a partie in it himſelfe, would haue ſound it an vpſpeakeable danger.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 13, 6,</note>It is a great heauineſſe for a man to looſe a louing friend, which was to him <hi>as his owne ſoule,</hi> as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaith. And yet this was <hi>Dauids</hi> caſe in the death of <hi>Ionathan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 18, 1, 3.</note> 
               <hi>whoſe ſoule was knit to the ſoule of Dauid,</hi> and they loued one another as their owne ſoules, and they made a couenant together. And how hee tooke it to heart, may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by that dolefull lamentation, that he maketh for him when he heard the tydings of his death; <hi>Woe is me for thee my brother Ionathan:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 1, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6,</note> 
               <hi>very kinde
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:20488:18"/>
haſt thou beene to me: thy loue to me was wonderful, paſsing the loue of women.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The loſſe of children by any meanes whatſoeuer, is a great griefe to kinde and louing parents, who haue born them with great paine and trauell, and brought them vp with much care and coſt. But to be depriued of them by vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely &amp; violent &amp; feareful death, is a griefe that cannot be expreſſed. None knoweth the greatnes of it, but they that haue felt it. And yet this hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallen euen y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deareſt of Gods children. <hi>Aaron,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 106, 16.</note> whom the Scripture calleth the <hi>Saint of the Lord,</hi> had his two ſons <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dab</hi> &amp; <hi>Abihu</hi> fearfully deſtroyed both in a mome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with fire from heauen.<note place="margin">Leuit. 10.2:</note> 
               <hi>Eli</hi> a good man,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 4 11:</note> had likewiſe his two ſons <hi>Hophni</hi> and <hi>Phinehas</hi> ſlaine in battell both on a day. <hi>Iob</hi> alſo,<note place="margin">Iob. 1, 2, 19.</note> whoſe godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe we haue heard before, had all his children, <hi>ſeuen ſonnes and three daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> pittifully ſlaine, &amp; cruſht in pieces with the fall of an houſe. But the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt griefe of all is, when a mans childe is taken away in ſome ſin, ſo as, beſides the death of the bodie, hee hath iuſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:20488:19"/>
cauſe to feare the death of the ſoule. And yet this was good <hi>Dauids</hi> caſe, in the loſſe of his <hi>Abſalom,</hi> which made him breake forth into ſuch paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate mourning as he did.<note place="margin">2. Sam. 18.33.</note> 
               <hi>O my ſon Abſalom, my ſonne, my ſonne Abſalom, would God I had dyed for thee, O Abſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom my ſonne, my ſonne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a great griefe for a man to bee depriued of the <hi>wife of his youth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 5, 18.</note> which hath long <hi>lyen in his boſome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 13, 6</note> which for many yeares hath beene vnto him as <hi>the louing hinde and pleaſant Roe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 5.19</note> in whoſe loue he hath ſo long delighted, and which was <hi>the pleaſure and deſire of his eyes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezech. 24, 16</note> And yet this befell thoſe two holy Patriarkes <hi>Abraham and Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, Abraham</hi> was depriued of his dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt <hi>Sara,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 23.2. and 35, 19</note> and <hi>Iacob</hi> of <hi>Rahel,</hi> whom he ſo much affected.</p>
            <p>There cannot be a greater affliction to a poore woman, then to looſe a kinde and louing husband, which was <hi>the vaile of her eyes</hi> in all places.<note place="margin">Gen. 20.16</note> But with the loſſe of an husband, to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reft of all meanes of maintenance, and expoſed to extreame pouertie, is ſuch
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:20488:19"/>
a croſſe as can hardly bee imagined. And yet wee haue examples euen of this kinde alſo. Poore <hi>Naomi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ruth 1.3.</note> was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of her husband in a ſtrange cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, where ſhe had few friends, and ſmall meanes, and her two ſonnes, which had taken them wiues there in the land of <hi>Moab,</hi> died alſo,<note place="margin">5.</note> ſo that ſhe was left alone and deſtitute of ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour? And how much ſhe was affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with this calamitie, may appeare by her ſpeeches,<note place="margin">20.</note> when ſhe returned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine into her owne country. <hi>Call me not Naomi,</hi> ſaith ſhe (that is beautifull) <hi>but call me Mara</hi> (that is bitter) <hi>for the Almightie hath giuen me much bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. I went out full,</hi>
               <note place="margin">21:</note> 
               <hi>and the Lord hath brought me home againe emptie: why then call yee me Naomi, ſeeing the Lord hath humbled mee, and the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie hath brought mee into aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</hi> So likewiſe the <hi>Prophets</hi> wife that dyed in the land of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Kin. 4.1.</note> beſides the loſſe of her husband, was left in great debt, and hauing nothing to pay, the mercileſſe creditour <hi>came to take her two ſonnes to be his bondmen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:20488:20"/>It is an vncomfortable thing to dy in child birth:<note place="margin">Gen. 35.17.18</note> and yet it was the caſe of <hi>Rahel Iacobs</hi> wife, who dyed <hi>in the paines of her labour:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sai. m. 4, 19, 20.</note> &amp; of <hi>Elies</hi> daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in lawe, who hearing that the <hi>arke of God was taken,</hi> and her husband and father in law were dead, <hi>bowed her ſelfe and trauelled, and in her trauell dyed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is feareful to dye a violent death, and yet it is a thing that hath happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned euen vnto thoſe that were deare vnto God.<note place="margin">1. Sam 4, 18</note> 
               <hi>Eli</hi> (of whom wee haue heard before) when he heard mention of the loſſe of Gods Arke, being hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie and vnweildie with age, <hi>fell back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward from his ſeat, and his necke was broken,</hi> and ſo he dyed. The <hi>Prophet</hi> of the Lord, that was ſent to cry againſt the altar,<note place="margin">1. Kin. 13, 24</note> which <hi>Ieroboam</hi> had made at <hi>Bethel,</hi> becauſe he kept not the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement which the Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded him, <hi>a lyon met him by the way and ſlew him, and his carkaiſe was caſt in the way.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Kin. 23.29</note> And good <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> who is ſo highly commended for his god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, was notwithſtanding ſlaine in the warres by <hi>Pharao Necho,</hi> king of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:20488:20"/>
               <hi>Egypt.</hi> Nay a man may be ſo far left to himſelfe, as he may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit ſuch a ſinne, wherby he may deſerue to be cut off by the ſword of the Magiſtrate, &amp; yet ſtill be the child of God. As the ſins y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> expreſſe law of God were to be puniſhed with death, if there had bin any Magiſtrat aboue him that had had power to inflict it. By all theſe particular inſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, &amp; many more that might be produced, it may appear, that there is not any kind of afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> children of God may be ſubiect to it: according to that enume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration which the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> maketh,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.35.</note> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaith, <hi>Who ſhal ſeparate vs from the loue of Chriſt, ſhal tribulation, or anguiſh or perſecution, or famine, or nakedneſſe, or perill or ſword, &amp;c.</hi> A man may bee ſubiect to all theſe miſeries, &amp; yet not be depriued of the loue of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But beſides all theſe outward afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the children of God may bee, and oftentimes are ſubiect to inward fear &amp; horror of conſcience, which as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Prou., 18.14.</note> is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt intolerable tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> can be indured <hi>The ſpirit of a man
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:20488:21"/>
wil ſuſtain his infirmitie: but a wounded ſpirit who can bear? Iob</hi> was not only af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted in his body and outward eſtate, but alſo troubled and wounded in his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, with the fearful apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Gods wrath. And therefore hee complaineth,<note place="margin">Iob. 6.4.</note> 
               <hi>that the arrowes of the Almightie were in him, the venime or poyſon whereof did drinke vp his ſpirit, and the terrours of God did fight, or ſet themſelues in array againſt him.</hi> And <hi>Dauid</hi> cryeth out,<note place="margin">Pſal. 22, 1.</note> 
               <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken mee, and art ſo farre from my health, and from the words of my roaring?</hi> And in another place he ſaith,<note place="margin">and 32.3.4</note> 
               <hi>When I held my tongue, my bones conſumed, when I roared all the day long. For thy hand was heauie v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon me day and night, and my moyſture is turned into the drought of ſummer.</hi> And in another place, he maketh ſuch a lamentable complaint, as if hee had beene brought to the very pit of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperation.<note place="margin">and 38.2.3.4.5, 6.7.8.</note> 
               <hi>Thine arrowes,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>ſticke faſt in me, and thy hand preſſeth me ſore. There is nothing ſound in my fleſh, becauſe of thine anger: neither is
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:20488:21"/>
there any reſt in my bones, by reaſon of my ſinne. For mine iniquities are gone ouer mine head and as a mightie bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den they are too heauie for mee. My wounds ſtincke, aad are corrupt becauſe of my fooliſhneſſe. I am bowed and croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged very ſore: I goe mourning all the day. For my reines are full of burning, and there is nothing ſound in my fleſh. I am weakened, and ſore broken: I roare for the very griefe of my heart, &amp;c.</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine,<note place="margin">and 130.1.</note> 
               <hi>Out of the deepe places haue I called vnto thee, O Lord:</hi> as if hee had beene euen in the bottome of hell. In a word, <hi>Hezekiah</hi> that good King complaineth, that beſides the ſickneſſe which God laid vpon his bodie, that brought him euen to deathes dore, <hi>the Lord had broken al his bones like a lyon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 38.13.14.</note> 
               <hi>and from day to night he made an end of him, and that he chattered like a crane or ſwallow, and mourned as a doue.</hi> By this we ſee, that euen the children of God doe many times wraſtle with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperation it ſelfe: and the Lord doth ſo long hide his face from them, as they ſeeme vtterly to be forſaken, and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:20488:22"/>
beginne to thinke, that <hi>his mercie is cleane gone for euer,</hi> as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, and that hee <hi>will bee fauourable no more.</hi> And therefore, the Church of God is compared to <hi>a lillie among thornes,</hi> to giue vs to vnderſtand, that though it be very louely &amp; beautifull in the ſight of God: yet it is ſubiect to many miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and accombred with many mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtations.</p>
            <p>But here it may be ſome will obiect, if the caſe bee ſo that the children of God be ſubiect to ſo many &amp; great af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, then it ſeemeth, that either their ſins are not fully forgiuen them, or elſe, that God is not iuſt in inflicting ſuch puniſhments vpon them. To this I anſwer,<note place="margin">Pſal. 103.3 Col. 2, 13 1, Iohn. 1, 7</note> that firſt, for the ſins of Gods children, they are all abſolutely forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. <hi>The hlood of Chriſt,</hi> as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Iſa 1, 8,</note> 
               <hi>doth clenſe vs from al ſin.</hi> So that though they <hi>be as ſcarlet,</hi> yet the Lord maketh them <hi>as white as ſnow,</hi> &amp; thogh they be <hi>red like crimſon,</hi> hee maketh them <hi>as woll.</hi>
               <note place="margin">and, 44, 22.</note> Yea the Lord <hi>putteth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way our tranſgreſsions like a cloud, and our ſinnes like a miſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mich. 7.19</note> 
               <hi>he ſubdueth our
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:20488:22"/>
iniquities, and caſteth them into the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of the Sea.</hi> So as they ſhall neuer riſe vp in iudgement againſt vs to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe or condemne vs. Againe, the Lord is <hi>righteous in all his waies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 145.17,</note> 
               <hi>&amp; holy in all his workes:</hi> and being <hi>Iudge of all the world,</hi> as <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaid, <hi>he muſt needs do right.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 18, 25</note> And foraſmuch as our <hi>Sauiour Chriſt</hi> hath ſatisfied Gods iuſtice for our ſins,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.24</note> &amp; hath <hi>borne them in his bodie on the croſſe:</hi> &amp; feing the Lord hauing puniſhed them once in Chriſt,<note place="margin">Non his pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitur in idem.</note> cannot iuſtly puniſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> again in vs: therfore, it muſt needs follow, that the miſeries wherunto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> children of God are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, are not puniſhments of their ſins, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord hath other ends for which he afflicteth them. Now the ends are many, but for order ſake, we will refer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to three heads. Some of them are in reſpect of Gad, ſome in reſpect of vs, &amp; ſome in reſpect of others. The end that God aimeth at in reſpect of himſelfe, is twofold. Firſt, therby to manifeſt &amp; ſet forth his owne glory As our Sauiour ſaid co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the man that was borne blind,<note place="margin">Iohn 9, 2, 3</note> that that affliction was laid vpon
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:20488:23"/>
him, neither for his owne ſinnes, nor for his fathers ſinnes, <hi>but that the workes of God might be ſhewed on him.</hi> And indeed no ſmall glory redoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vnto God by the afflictions of his children. As the power of God is more magnified and declared in aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, then euer it could be in proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie. For that which the Lord ſaid to the <hi>Apoſtle Paul</hi> concerning outward afflictions,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 12.9</note> 
               <hi>My power is made perfite through weakeneſſe.</hi> For when we are in proſperitie, &amp; ſee no euill, we ſeeme not to ſtand need of Gods helpe. But when God deliuereth vs out of troble, then is his power manifeſted, and then haue we occaſion offered to glorifiie him.<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.15</note> As it is ſaid in the <hi>Pſalme. Call vpon me in the day of trouble and I will deliuer thee, and thou ſhalt glorifie mee.</hi> Yea though the Lord for cauſes beſt knowne to himſelfe, doe not deliuer his children out of their miſeries and tribulations: yet this is no ſmall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of glory vnto him,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 1, 4. 1. Pet. 1.8</note> that in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of them all he miniſtreth comfort vnto them, and maketh them cheerful,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:20488:23"/>
and cauſeth them to <hi>reioyce with ioy vnſpeakeable, and glorious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly to declare his anger and indignation againſt ſinne, that when the wicked ſhall ſee that Gods deareſt children, if they take libertie to ſinne, doe not eſcape the rod, they may know what themſelues are to looke for at his hands, according to that ſpeech of the <hi>Apoſtle Peter, If Iudgement firſt begin at the houſe of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 4, 17.</note> 
               <hi>what ſhall bee the end of them that obey not the Goſpell of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ends that God aimeth at in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of vs, are diuerſe. Firſt to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect and chaſten vs for our faults. As the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith, <hi>When we are iudged, we are chaſtened of the Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.32.</note> As a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that hath care of his childe, if he ſee him take euill courſes, will correct him to bring him to amendment: ſo our moſt mercifull father will not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer his children to continue in ſinne,<note place="margin">Heb. 12, 6.</note> but vſeth corrections to reclame them. Secondly, to try and exerciſe the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that are in them, and to make them more conſpicuous. Not as though the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:20488:24"/>
Lord were ignorant of them. For he that made them, muſt needes know what is in them. And therefore, it is ſaid of our <hi>Sauiour Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 2, 24, 25,</note> that how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer many profeſſed to beleeue in him; yet he <hi>did not commit himſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, becauſe hs knew them all, and had no neede that any man ſhould teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie of man, for he knew what was in man.</hi> But he doth it, that men may knowe themſelues, and that it may appeare vnto others, what excellent things God hath wrought in them. Thus ſaid <hi>Iob</hi> of his afflictons, he knew they were no puniſhments of his ſinnes, as his friends would haue perſwaded him, but tryals of his faith and patience. <hi>He knoweth my way,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 23, 10,</note> ſaith he, <hi>and try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth me, and I ſhall come forth like the gold.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet 1, 6, 7</note> And the <hi>Apoſtle Peter</hi> ſaith, that the children of God are <hi>in heauineſſe through manifold tentations, that the tryall of their faith, being much more precious then gold that periſheth, might be found to their praiſe and honour and glory at the appearing of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> God will not ſuffer the graces of his
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:20488:24"/>
children to lye idle and to ruſt in them, but by afflictions will exerciſe them and bring them to light. As Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith well.<note n="a" place="margin">Non eſt paena crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, ſed vittu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis examen. De Civ. Dei lib. 4. cap. 3.</note> Affliction is not a puniſhment of ſinne, but a tryall of our vertue. And firſt, the faith of Gods children is hereby tryed and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted. When a man is in no danger nor miſery it is an eaſie matter for him to beleeue, but when he groaneth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the burden of affliction, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth euen to be quite forſaken of the Lord, then by the power of his faith to cry with <hi>Dauid, My God, my God,</hi> and with <hi>Iob, though he ſlay me, yet will I truſt in him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 22, 1. Iob. 13.15.</note> is a matter of great diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie. Againe, their Chriſtian courage appeareth.<note n="b" place="margin">Dulce bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> expe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis.</note> We thinke we are ſtrong e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, till we be put to the trial. <hi>(a)</hi> As many vaine cowards in the middeſt of their cups,<note n="c" place="margin">Marcet ſine aduerſario virtus, Guber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natorem in tempeſtate, in acie militem intelligas. De diuina proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentia.</note> wil make great boaſt of their valor, but when they come into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> field, they dare not looke the enemy in the face. <hi>Seneca,</hi> an heathen man, that neuer knew what y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> valor of a true <hi>Chriſtian</hi> meant, could yet ſay of moral fortitude <hi>(a)</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it withereth &amp; becometh feeble if
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:20488:25"/>
it haue not an aduerſarie to encounter withall. The skill of a Pilot is beſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in the greateſt tempeſt, and the courage of a Soldier in the hotteſt skirmiſh. So the fortitude of a <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Soldier</hi> apeareth moſt in the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt and heauieſt affliction. How can it bee knowne what courage a man hath to endure ſickneſſe and pouertie, &amp;c. if he alwaies haue his health, and abound in riches. Moreouer their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience is by this means made knowne. <hi>Patience</hi> is a virtue which is alwayes neceſſarie for vs, but if it be not exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed we ſhall haue little vſe of it. As when a ſword is ruſted in the ſheath, a man may be wounded by his aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry before he can draw it forth: ſo when patience is not tryed, the Deuill may wound a man to death, before hee be able to defend himſelfe with it. Laſt of all, by this meanes their loue to God is moſt of all declared. It is not any thing worth for a man to loue God, when all things proſper with him, &amp; ſucceed according to his owne deſire. Now if a man ſhould not loue
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:20488:25"/>
God then, euen in the iudgement of the deuill, it were pittie of his life. For he could ſay when the Lord commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Iob. Doth Iob feare God for nought?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob, 1.9.10.</note> 
               <hi>haſt thou not made an hedge about him, and about his houſe, and about all that he hath on euery ſide? thou haſt bleſſed the worke of his hands,, and his ſubſtance is increaſed in the land.</hi> Nay he that ſhall onely loue God in this reſpect, may ſeeme to loue him for what will you giue me rather then for his owne ſake. But he that cleaueth vnto God in the time of affliction, when all things goe croſſe with him, that is a token of true loue indeed. Thus we ſee how the graces of Gods children are manifeſted in affliction, more then they could be in proſperity. As brickes if they be not throughly hardned in the fire, will by and by be diſſolued; if they come into the water. So vnles the graces of Gods children be continually exerciſed, the leaſt affliction that is will ouercome them. Spices neuer giue a ſweeter ſmell, then when they are beaten to powder: ſo the graces of God
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:20488:26"/>
in his children are neuer ſo fragrant &amp; odoriferous, as whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are as it were pounded by affliction, according to that ſpeech of the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom: 5.3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>Tribulation bringeth forth patience, and patience ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, and experience hope, &amp;c.</hi> Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto agreeth that ſaying of S. <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Non fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git in bonis perferendi to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerandique virtutem, nec eradicat ex a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimo pieta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, ſed exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citatam facit foecundio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem. De Civ. Dei lib. 1. ca. 13.</note> Afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> danteth not the patience &amp; fortitude of them that be good, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther rooteth godlineſſe out of their minds, but by exerciſing of it, maketh it more fruitfull. And that of <hi>Bernard,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Ignis afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat, non ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, in Pſal. 91. Serm 5.</note> The fire of affliction trieth the graces of the godly, but it doth not conſume them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the Lord afflicteth his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to preuent ſin to come. There is in the beſt of vs ſuch a maſſe of corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as that vpon euery occaſion wee are apt and proane to fall into ſinne: and therefore, for preuenting thereof, it is neceſſary that the Lord ſhould af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict vs. As a skilfull <hi>Phyſition</hi> many times preſcribeth medicins to preſerue from ſickenes: ſo doth the Lord vſe affliction to preſerue his children from ſinne.<note place="margin">Matth. 9.12</note> 
               <hi>They that be whole</hi> (as our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:20488:26"/>
Chriſt</hi> ſaith) <hi>neede not a Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> So, if wee were ſound indeede, and had no corruption in vs, we ſhould not neede to bee dealt withall in this manner. But being corrupted and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempered as wee are, wee ſtand neede to bee purged and let bloud by affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>Foutthly, by afflictions the Lord doth giue vs ſome comfortable teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of the reſurrection to a better life. For ſeeing the godly are for the moſt, in this life ſo euill intreated, they may aſſure themſelues, that in the life to come, there ſhall be a bleſſed change and alteration,<note place="margin">Apoc. 21.4.</note> wherein <hi>God ſhall wipe away all teares from their eyes, and there ſhalbe no more death, nor ſorrow, neither ſhall there be any more paine.</hi> But,<note place="margin">Lu. 22.28, 29 30.</note> 
               <hi>they that haue continued with Chriſt Ieſus in his tentations, ſhall haue a kingdome appointed vnto them by him, that they may eat &amp; drink at his table in his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, &amp;c.</hi> This is that which <hi>Abraham</hi> told the rich glutto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being in hel in tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>Son,</hi> ſaith he,<note place="margin">Luke 16.25</note> 
               <hi>remember that thou in thy life time receiuedſt thy pleaſures,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:20488:27"/>
and likewiſe Lazarus pains: now therfore is he comforted, &amp; thou art tormented.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fiftly, by afflictions wee are made conformable vnto <hi>Chriſt.</hi> For he was not exempt from the Croſſe, as one ſaith wel.<note n="a" place="margin">Deus filium vnum habuit ſine peccato, nullum ſine flagello. Hebr. 5.9 Ma th. 3.17 Cal Inſtitut. lib. 3. cap. 8. ſect. 1.</note> God had one ſonne with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſinne, but none without affliction. Though he were <hi>the author of eternall ſaluation to al that obey him:</hi> yet he was <hi>conſecrate by afflictions.</hi> Yea albeit he were the <hi>beloued Sonne of God, in whom he is well pleaſed:</hi> yet we ſee his Father was ſo far from cockering and pampe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of him, that we may truely ſay he was not onely exerciſed with afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, whiles he was vpon the earth: but his whole life was nothing elſe but a continuall croſſe.<note place="margin">Iohn 15.20</note> Why then ſhould we looke to be exempted from that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition which Chriſt our head was to vndergoe? eſpecially ſeeing hee did vndergoe it for our ſakes, that in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe hee might giue vs an example of patience. And therefore the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> teacheth vs, that all the children of God are <hi>predeſtinated</hi> to this end,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.29</note> 
               <hi>that they might be made like to the Image of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:20488:27"/>
him.</hi> In a word, by afflictions the Lord doth ſeale vnto vs the aſſurance of our adoption. For as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith, <hi>Whom the Lord loueth hee chaſteneth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">He. 11:6, 7, 8.</note> 
               <hi>and he ſcourgeth euery ſonne that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth. If yee endure chaſtening, God offereth himſelfe vnto you as ſonnes: for what ſonne is it whom the Father cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteneth not? If therefore yee be without correction, whereof all are partakers, then are yee baſtards and not ſonnes.</hi> Where wee are taught, that wee can gather no greater teſtimony, that wee are the ſonnes of God, than from the louing corrections which hee layeth vpon vs.</p>
            <p>Laſt of all, there is a good end of our afflictions in reſpect of others. If wee be conſtant and couragious vnder the croſſe, our example is a notable en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement vnto others to treade in our ſteppes. If wee bee fearefull and faint-hearted, others may learne what frailty there is in man,<note place="margin">Rom. 12.15 Hecr. 13.3</note> and may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by be moued to pitty vs, as if it were their owne caſe, as alſo to comfort vs, and to pray for vs: and to watch more
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:20488:28"/>
carefully &amp; dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly ouer themſelues. To conclude, the way to euerlaſting glory, is by this meanes as it were chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked out. For hereby all men may ſee, that <hi>Whoſoeuer will liue godly in Chriſt Ieſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.12.</note> 
               <hi>muſt ſuffer perſecution:</hi> and that <hi>Through many tribulations we muſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the kingdome of Heauen.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act.s 14.22.</note> And thus wee ſee the poynt is ſufficiently cleared, that afflictions to Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are no puniſhments of their ſins, but that the Lord ſendeth them for many other good ends and purpoſes.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> The vſe of this Doctrine is very profitable. Firſt, it ſerueth to teach euery one of vs, to <hi>iudge wiſely,</hi> as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, <hi>of the poore, and thoſe that are afflicted.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 41 1.</note> There is a corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in our nature, which maketh vs raſhly conclude, when wee ſee a man afflicted with ſome heauie croſse, that ſurely it is GODS iudgement vpon him for his ſinne. So dealt the <hi>Barbarians</hi> with the <hi>Apoſtle Paul,</hi> when they ſawe a <hi>Viper</hi> leape vpon him, and hang vpon his hand, they ſaide preſently amongſt themſelues:
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:20488:28"/>
               <hi>This man ſurely is a murtherer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 28.3, 4,</note> 
               <hi>whom though hee haue eſcaped the Sea, yet vengeance hath not ſuffred to liue.</hi> Yea this corruption will euen creep into the beſt of vs all, if we do not endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to keepe it out. As wee ſee in <hi>Iobs</hi> friends, who though they were otherwiſe men of great knowledge, and (no doubt) godly: yet when they ſaw the ſtrange afflictions that GOD had brought vpon him, they by and by, with one conſent, paſse their cenſure vpon him, That he was an hypocrite, and that GOD had now found him out.<note place="margin">Iob 8, 4,</note> As <hi>Bildad</hi> tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth him plainely, that his ſonnes had ſinned againſt GOD, and therefore that hee had iuſtly ſent them <hi>To the place of their iniquitie.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 11.6.</note> And <hi>Zophar</hi> bids him know, <hi>that God had forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten him for his iniquitie.</hi> Yea <hi>Eliphaz</hi> commeth to particulars with him. <hi>Is not</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>thy wickednes great,</hi>
               <note place="margin">and 22.5, 6, 7, 9.</note> 
               <hi>and thine iniquities innumerable? For thou haſt taken the pledge from thy brother for nought, and ſpoiled the cloathes of the naked. To ſuch as were weary, thou
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:20488:29"/>
haſt not giuen water to drinke, and haſt withdrawne bread from the hungrie. Thou haſt caſt out widowes empty, and the armes of the fatherleſſe were broken.</hi> And where we ſee, he is not afraid to charge <hi>Iob</hi> with oppreſſion and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercifulnes, as if theſe had beene the cauſes of his calamitie. And the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of our <hi>Sauiour Chriſt,</hi> when they ſaw a man that was borne blinde, they ſtraitway imagined, that it was either for his owne or his parents ſins. But we muſt know,<note place="margin">Iohn 9.1.2</note> that euery croſſe is not a purſuing of a man for ſinne, as our <hi>Sauiour</hi> teacheth in the Goſpel, when he ſaid to them that ſhewed him of the <hi>Galileans,</hi> whoſe bloud <hi>Pilate</hi> had mingled with their owne ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces:<note place="margin">Lu. 13.1, 2, 3, 4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>Suppoſe yee, that theſe Galileans were greater ſinners then all other Gali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leans, becauſe they haue ſuffered ſuch things. I tell you nay &amp;c. Or thinke ye, that thoſe eighteene, vpon whom the To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer in Siloam fell and ſlew them, were ſinners aboue all that dwel in Ieruſalem? I tell you nay, &amp;c.</hi> And therefore, if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of vs haue beene fooliſh this way,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:20488:29"/>
and haue thought wickedly and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitably of our brethren, when wee haue ſeene them viſited by the hand of God, let vs learne henceforth, as <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſaith, <hi>to lay our hand vpon our mouthes, Pro</hi> 30.32. leſt we condemne the generation of Gods children, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.15. Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> hath a moſt excellent ſaying to this purpoſe: Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſaith hee, the godly and the wicked be alike afflicted, yet they are diſtinct the one from the other, there<note n="a" place="margin">Manet diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimilitudo paſſorum in ſimilitudine paſsionum.</note> remaineth an vnlikeneſſe of the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferers, in the likeneſſe of their ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings. For, as vnder one and the ſame fire, golde ſhineth and gliſtereth, and chaffe ſmoaketh: and vnder one and the ſame flaile, the ſtrawe is broken is pieces, and the corne is purged: ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are the lees therefore mingled with the oyle, becauſe they are ſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned out in one and the ſame preſſe: So one and the ſame violence ruſhing vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the godly and the wicked, tryeth,<note n="b" place="margin">Tantum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, non qualia, ſed qualis quiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que patia ur. De Ciu. Dei lib. 1. cap. 8</note> purifieth and melteth the one, but it damneth, deſtroyeth, and vtterly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doeth the other. <hi>h</hi> So great a matter it
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:20488:30"/>
is, not what things one ſuffereth, but how he is qualified that ſuffereth. For one and the ſame motion cauſeth the dung to ſtincke horribly, and the oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to ſmell moſt ſweetely: So that afflictions are like the red Sea, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> were drowned, and the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſaued.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, it ſerueth to comfort all Gods children in the middeſt of the greateſt afflictions that can befall them. It is the infirmitie and weaknes of our nature to thinke, that afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is a token of Gods anger, and that if any extraordinary croſſe doe befall vs, we preſently feare that God hath forſaken vs. But as we heard already, though God afflict vs with many and heauie croſſes, yet we are neuer the leſſe deare vnto him, neyther doth hee loue vs any whit the leſſe. An Heathen man, that neuer had expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of the loue of God to his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, had yet a glimmering of the trueth of this point.<note n="a" place="margin">Seneca Dc diuin. Prouid.</note> Doſt thou not ſee, ſaith he, that fathers loue their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren farre otherwiſe then mothers doe?
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:20488:30"/>
They would haue their children ſtirred vp betimes to vndergoe labor &amp; toile, &amp; cauſe them to ſweat, yea ſomtimes to weepe. But mothers deſire to cheriſh them in their boſoms, &amp; to keep them in couert &amp; ſhelter: they would neuer haue them weepe, they would neuer haue them ſad, they would neuer haue them take paines. In like maner (ſaith he) God hath a fatherly affection to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards good men, and loueth them not effeminately, but manfully, and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſeth them with labors, with ſorrows, with loſſes, that ſo they may gather true ſtrength and hardneſſe: So that the greater that our afflictions are, the better may wee be perſwaded of the loue of God: yea the more comfort we may take in them. For God hauing promiſed,<note place="margin">1, Cor. 10, 13</note> that <hi>Hee will not ſuffer vs to be tempted aboue that wee are able:</hi> we may aſſure our ſelues that God ſeeth wee haue ſtrength to beare them, or elſe he would not put vs to encounter with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. When a <hi>Captain</hi> hath a piece of ſeruice weighty and full of danger, hee will not ſend a coward or a white-liuered
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:20488:31"/>
fellow about it, but hee ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth choice of thoſe that are ſtouteſt, and of whoſe valour and courage hee hath had moſt experience, and to them he committeth the charge of that bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſines. So dealeth the Lord with vs. In his great wiſedome and mercie hee proportioneth his afflictions, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that meaſure of ſtrength, which hee ſeeth in vs. When a <hi>Phyſition</hi> hath to deale with a Patient that is of a ſtrong conſtitution, hee miniſtreth to him ſtrong purgations: But if hee be weake and feeble, hee preſcribeth for him milder potions. In like manner our heauenly <hi>Phyſition</hi> maketh the cup of our affl ctions more bitter or more milde, as hee knoweth hee hath giuen vs ability to beare the ſame. And ſo long as hee ſtrengtheneth vs by his glorious power, wee neede not care what croſſes wee meete withall: for wee may be ſure they ſhall not hurt vs. For, as ſo many riuers which daily do runne into the Sea,<note place="margin">Sen. de diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na Prouid.</note> and ſuch aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of raine that falleth continually into it from the Cloudes, and ſuch a
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:20488:31"/>
multitude of fountaines that ſpring from the middle of the earth, doe not change, no nor any whit abate or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh the ſalt ſauour thereof: ſo the violence and force of afflictions doth not alter the minde of a violent man, but he abideth in his eſtate, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer befalleth, hee bringeth it into his owne colour. And on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſide, there is no greater cauſe of diſcomfort, then when wee are alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether free from aiflictions. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore one calleth a ſecure life, which is not ſubiect to croſſes, the dead Sea, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming, that when a man hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to ſtirre him vp, and pricke him forward, nothing to trie the conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and firmeneſſe of his minde,<note place="margin">Non eſt tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quilitas, mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia eſt. Sene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca epiſt. 68.</note> but lieth bur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed in idleneſſe, it is not tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility but a dead calme.</p>
            <p>Againe, this is no ſmall argument of comfort, that God beholdeth vs in all our troubles and afflictions, as it is ſaid of the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 2.25</note> when they groand vnder the bondage of <hi>Pharao,</hi> that <hi>God looked on them, and had reſpect vnto them.</hi> Though they might thinke,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:20488:32"/>
in regard of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miſerable ſlauery which they indured, that God had quite for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten them, and his promiſe made to them and their fathers: yet it was o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, his eye did ſtill behold them. Neithet doth the Lord looke vpon vs, as an idle beholder, or as one that taketh pleaſure to ſee our miſery, but with compaſsion and a tender regard. As hee ſaith in the former caſe,<note place="margin">Exod, 3.7.</note> 
               <hi>I haue ſurely ſeene the trouble of my people which are in Aegypt, and haue heard their cry, becauſe of their taske-mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,</hi>
               <note place="margin">8.</note> 
               <hi>and I know their ſorrowes. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I am come downe to deliuer them, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">9.</note> And <hi>loe, the crie of the children of Iſrael is come vnto me, and I haue alſo ſeene the oppreſsion, wherewith the Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians oppreſſe them.</hi> Where we ſee, that the Lord taketh to heart the affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of his children,<note place="margin">Iudg. 10 19 zach. 2.8</note> 
               <hi>And his verie ſoule is grieued for their miſerie,</hi> and it goeth as neare him,<note place="margin">Pſalme 56.8</note> as if a man ſhould <hi>touch the apple of his eye.</hi> He regardeth their ſighs and groans,<note place="margin">Malac. 3.16</note> and their <hi>teares hee putteth in his bottell:</hi> hee regiſtreth their words and complaints,<note place="margin">Exod. 2 23</note> 
               <hi>There is a
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:20488:32"/>
Booke of remembrance written for them that feare him,</hi> and all their <hi>cries come vp to him.</hi> It is true, that the Lord ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſeemeth to forget &amp; neglect his children in the time of trouble. As our <hi>Sauior Chriſt</hi> being in the ſhip with his Diſciples, was aſleepe, till the ſhip was couered with waues, and they were all like to periſh.<note place="margin">Iohn 11 6</note> When he heard that <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus</hi> his friend whom hee loued, was ſicke, he did not preſently goe to viſite him, &amp; to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort his ſiſters, but abode ſtil two dayes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place where he was, ſo as <hi>Lazarus</hi> was dead &amp; buried be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he came there. But when hee hath ſufficiently tryed &amp; humbled them, he returneth &amp; ſpeedily comforteth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and ſo diſpoſeth of their afflictions, as hee alwayes enableth them to get the victory. For,<note place="margin">Orig. de prin. lib, 3. cap. 2.</note> as they that had the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſight of the wraſtlings and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates among the Heathen, did not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the combatants to begin the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict hand ouer head, nor arme them confuſedly, all alike: but making di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent examination, as they ſaw mens bodies and ages, they were carefull
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:20488:33"/>
to match like with like, and to furniſh them with weapons fitte for them: In like ſort, the prouidence of God diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth and ordereth after a moſt equal maner, all thoſe that deſcend into the conflicts of this life, ſo as one encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treth with the fleſh, another with po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerty, another with ſickenes, another with infamy, another with perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and putteth vpon euery one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diuers kinds of armor, and furniſheth them with greater or leſſer ſtrength, as may inable them to ouercome the eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my that is appointed for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For God is not like the maſter of the games be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſpoken of, who when hee hath ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the parties, departeth out of the wraſtling place to behold the combat with the reſt. But the Lord ſtandeth by them ſtill, and aideth and aſſiſteth them at euery turne, and continually ſuccoureth them that are weaker with greater ſtrength.</p>
            <p>And heerein the Lord dealeth with his children, as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> dealt with his brethren when they came into <hi>Egipt</hi> to buy corne. For as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> himſelfe was
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:20488:33"/>
many wayes tried of the Lord, before he was made Ruler of the Land: ſo he likewiſe many wayes tryed and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed his brethren before hee would make himſelfe knowne vnto them, or acknowledge them to be his brethren. Firſt, he tryed them,<note place="margin">Geneſ. 42.7. et cetera ad 24.</note> whether they had truly repented, and were touched with remorſe for the iniury they had done to him, in that ſo cruelly and vnna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally they ſolde him into <hi>Aegypt:</hi> Secondly, hee tryed them, whether they had attempted any ſuch thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Beniamin</hi> his brother German,<note place="margin">Ibid. ver. 20</note> in that hee enioyned them to bring him with them the next time, that hee might ſee him: Thirdly,<note place="margin">Gen 43.34</note> when they had brought him, hee ſhewed extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary kindeneſſe to him aboue the reſt, giuing him fiue times ſo great a portion as hee did any of them, and all to trie whether they did enuy him or no: Fourthly, he tryed them whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they loued their brother <hi>Benia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min</hi> ſo well, that when hee alone was detained,<note place="margin">Gen. 44.1. et cetera ad 14 and 33.</note> they would all for his ſake come backe againe from their iourny.
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:20488:34"/>
Laſt of all, he tried them whether they loued their fathet ſo intirely, as y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they would not return home without <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iamin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid. verſe 17, et cet.</note> which they knew would be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable griefe vnto their father. All this while no doubt his brethren were in great perplexity &amp; much troubled; and ſtill <hi>Ioſeph</hi> made as though he had not regarded them. But his bowels did earne within him towards them, and his heart was aſmuch grieued as theirs, inſomuch as twice he was conſtrained to turne from them and weep.<note place="margin">Gen. 42.24 and 43 30 and 45.1, 2, 3</note> And at the laſt he could refrain no longer, but he cried out, <hi>I am Ioſeph your brother.</hi> So likewiſe <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> our bleſſed <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth 28.10 Heb. 2.11</note> who is not aſhamed <hi>to call vs his Brethren,</hi> doth ſuffer vs to be exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with many &amp; grieuous afflictions, and ſeemeth ſometimes as though he cared not for vs: but yet in the meane while,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 11 8</note> 
               <hi>his repentings are rolled together,</hi> and at the laſt, when he hath ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tryed vs, hee will manifeſt himſelfe vnto vs to our vnſpeakeable comfort. According as himſelfe ſaith, <hi>Hee that loueth mee ſhall be loued of my Father,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 14.21</note>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:20488:34"/>
               <hi>and I will loue him, and will ſhew mine owne ſelfe to him:</hi> That is as one well noteth, I will loue him by trying his loue and patience, and when I haue tryed him, I will manifeſt my ſelfe vnto him. And though peraduenture this manifeſtation ſhall not bee by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie outwatd deliuerance in this life: yet at the day of Iudgement hee will acknowledge them openly in the ſight of men and Angells. Then hee ſhall not be able to containe himſelfe anie longer, but ſhall ſay vnto vs with a loude voyce, ſo as all the world ſhall heare. <hi>I am Ieſus your Brother, Come yee bleſſed of my Father, inherite the Kingdome prepared for you from the foundations of the world. Matt.</hi> 25.34. For, as the <hi>Aegyptians and all the houſe of Pharaoh heard the voyce of Ioſeph,</hi> when hee reuealed himſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Brethren, <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 45.2. So in the day of Iudgement, when <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhall manifeſt himſelfe to his brethren, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth, and all the <hi>Angells</hi> in heauen ſhall heare his voyce: yea all the damned, &amp; the whole houſe of hell
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:20488:35"/>
ſhall heare it, and ſhall gnaſh their teeth for anger: and gnaw their tongs for griefe of heart to ſee thoſe whom they ſometimes had in deriſion, and in a parable of reproach, whoſe life they thought to be madnes, and their end without honour,<note place="margin">Wiſd. 5.3, 4, 5</note> to be now coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted among the children of God, and to haue their portion amongſt the Saints.</p>
            <p>Finally, this is another argument of vnſpeakeable comfort to the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, that the greater their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions are, the greater ſhal their glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie be.<note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.14.</note> As the <hi>Apoſtle Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>If ye be rayled vpon for the name of Chriſt</hi> (and it is true likewiſe of all other affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions) <hi>bleſſed are yee, for the Spirite of glorie, and of God reſteth vpon you.</hi> And heereof we haue a worthy example in <hi>Ioſeph</hi> before named. For, after the manifold and great calamities which he indured ſo many yeares, he was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted by <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and as himſelfe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth,<note place="margin">Gene. 45.8</note> was made <hi>Lord of all his houſe, and Ruler through all the land of Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt.</hi> And it is worthy to be noted,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:20488:35"/>
that for ſome thirteene yeares where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he was afflicted, he was exalted, and ruled in <hi>Aegypt</hi> for the ſpace of foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore yeares, as may eaſily be gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out of the Story.<note place="margin">Gen. 37.2 and 41.46</note> For hee was ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenteene yeares olde, when his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren ſolde him away:<note place="margin">and 50.22.</note> hee was thirtie yeares olde when hee was aduaunced by <hi>Pharaoh:</hi> and he liued Gouernour of the land of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> till hee were an hundred and ten yeares olde. Beſides, ſuch was the goodneſſe of God vnto him, that for the ſeueral miſeries which hee ſuffered, hee receiued a ſeuerall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. For the hatred of his brethren hee obtained the fauour of the King and his Nobles.<note place="margin">Gen. 37.19</note> For the contempt and ſcorne which his brethren heaped vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, calling him Dreamer, &amp;c.<note place="margin">and 42.6</note> he was worſhipped of them, with their faces downe to the ground. For the particoloured coate which they ſtript him of,<note place="margin">Gen. 37.23</note> when they caſt him into the pit, he was arayed by <hi>Pharaoh</hi> with a princely roabe of fine linnen.<note place="margin">and 41.42</note> In ſtead of the fetters wherewith he was bound in priſon, <hi>Pharaoh</hi> put his own ring on
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:20488:36"/>
his hand, and a chaine of golde about his necke. In ſteade of the priſon and dungeon where he lay, he was ſet vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Kings beſt Chariot ſaue one, and carried in great pomp throughout the cittie. Whereas before he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned of all men, as a ſtranger, as a ſeruant and a priſoner, hee is now ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored of all men, by bowing the knee at the Kings commaundement. In a word, in ſteade of his fathers houſe, from which he was exiled and bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, he had dominion in all the land of <hi>Aegypt.</hi> So true is that ſaying euen of an heathen man,<note n="a" place="margin">quanto plus tormenti, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o plus erit gloriae. Sene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a de diuin. Prouid.</note> The greater tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment a man indureth, the greater ſhall be his glory afterwards. But howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the Lord doth not alwayes deale thus with his children in this life: yet in the life to come, without all que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, they ſhall finde the truth of that comfortable promiſe, deliuered by the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.17</note> 
               <hi>Our light affliction which is but for a moment, cauſeth vnto vs a far more excellent and eternall weight of glorie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> Thirdly, this Doctrine ſerueth to admoniſh vs, that ſeeing affliction is
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:20488:36"/>
the lot and portion of Gods children in this life, that therefore wee ſhould prepare for it before it come. The Lord will not haue his children come to Heauen in a pleaſant way, that is ſtrewed with ruſhes, as it were, but <hi>through many tribulations wee muſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into his kingdome.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 514.22</note> As <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith well,<note n="a" place="margin">Non eſt i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doneus ad proemium, qui nondum paratus eſt ad patibulum. De coena Dom. Ser. 6</note> He is not meet for the crowne that is not yet prepared for the croſſe. And therefore it is good for vs to arme our ſelues before hand, that when they come they may not hitte vs on the bare. Wee muſt bee carefull to ſtore vp grace and comfort againſt a rainie day, that whatſoeuer ſhall befall vs, wee may bee prouided to beare it. In our beſt eſtate, wee muſt put our ſelues in a readineſſe to ſuffer aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, whenſoeuer GOD ſhall ſend it. In our greateſt abundance, it is good for vs to thinke of want: in our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie, it is good to looke for cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie: and in our perfecteſt health to remember that ſickeneſſe may come. There is nothing that maketh all af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction more bitter and grieuous vnto
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:20488:37"/>
vs, then becauſe it taketh vs many times on the blind ſide, before we ſee it, or dreame of it. Whereas miſerie that is fore-ſeene and premeditated, doth little hurt vs. Affliction is like the <hi>Baſiliske,</hi> of which it is written, that if it ſee a man before hee ſee it, it killeth him; but if hee ſee it firſt, it hath no power to hurt him. So affliction is moſt terrible to thoſe whom it findeth vnprepared. <hi>Seneca,</hi> though an Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then man, hath ſpoken well to this purpoſe:<note n="a" place="margin">Si non quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid fieri po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, pro futu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro habes, das in te vires re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus aduerſis, quas infregi quiſquis prior videt de tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l cap. 11</note> If (ſaith hee) thou doeſt not make account, that whatſoeuer can befall, may come vnto thee, thou giueſt aduerſitie power and ſtrength againſt thee, which, whoſoeuer ſeeth firſt, hath weakened and abated. And in an other place:<note n="b" place="margin">Sapiens aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſueſcit futuris malis, et quae alii diu pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endo leu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciunt, hic leuia facit diu cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tando Epi. 77</note> A wiſe man ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtometh himſelfe to future euills, and thoſe things which other men make eaſie by long ſuffering, hee ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth eaſie by foreſeeing.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, it teacheth vs to be patient in all the afflictions that God layeth vpon vs, becauſe they are his louing corrections, in regard of our daily falls
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:20488:37"/>
and infirmities. We may not ſay with <hi>Iob,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 6.2, 3</note> 
               <hi>Oh that my griefe were well weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and my miſeries were layd together in the ballance:</hi>
               <note place="margin">and 34.6</note> 
               <hi>For it would now bee heauier then the ſand of the Sea. And my wound is grieuous without my ſinne:</hi> But rather acknowledge, that we haue deſerued farre greater puniſhment, as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Pſalme 130.3</note> 
               <hi>If thou Lord ſtraitly mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt our iniquities, O Lord, who ſhall ſtand?</hi> If God ſhould deale with the beſt of vs according to our deſerts, we were neuer able to abide it. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith well,<note n="a" place="margin">Suſtinete virgam corri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientem, ne ſentiatis mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leum conte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentem. In pſ. 91. ſerm. 9</note> It is good for vs to beare the rodde of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, leſt we feele the hammer of confuſion. The more wee ſtruggle and ſtriue vnder the hand of God, the leſſe we preuaile, and the more we prouoke him to diſpleaſure, &amp; cauſe him to vſe harder courſes againſt vs. As a father, hauing an vnruly ſonne, that will not take correction, binds him to a forme. But the ſooner wee yeelde and ſubmit our ſelues to his will, and kiſſe his rod, the ſooner we ſhall be deliuered.</p>
            <p>Laſt of all, it ſerueth to reprooue the <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>5</label>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:20488:38"/>
profane wretches of the world, who inſult ouer the children of God in their miſeries: and doe not ſticke blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly to ſay,<note place="margin">Mal. 3, 14, 15</note> 
               <hi>What profite</hi> haue theſe holy fellowes <hi>by keeping Gods comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, or by walking humbly before the Lord of Hoſtes?</hi> Wee neuer regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Gods ſeruice, but <hi>haue wrought wickedneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ierem. 12.1</note> 
               <hi>and tempted GOD all our liues,</hi> and yet <hi>we are ſet vp and deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</hi> Wee haue <hi>rebelliouſly tranſgreſſed,</hi> euen from our cradles, and yet <hi>our wayes doe proſper, and we haue wealth at will.</hi> But let all ſuch vngodly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons know, firſt, that it is a grieuous ſinne, to adde affliction to thoſe that are in miſerie. For howſoeuer God do many times ſeuerely correct thoſe that tranſgreſſe his Lawe, though they be neuer ſo deare vnto him, yet hee will not allow the wicked to inſult ouer them, no more then a father that whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth his ſonne for his faults, will ſuffer his ſeruants ſpitefully to taunt and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach him. Againe, the children of God, though they walke neuer ſo vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly before the Lord, yet their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:20488:38"/>
is not in this life.<note place="margin">1 Iohn 3.2 2 Tim. 4.8</note> 
               <hi>It doth not yet appeare what they ſhall be.</hi> But there <hi>is a crowne of righteouſnes laide vp for them</hi> againſt the day of Iudgement: &amp; when <hi>Chriſt which is their life ſhall appeare,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Coloſſ. 3.4</note> 
               <hi>then ſhall they alſo appeare with him in glory.</hi> And for themſelues, though their proſperitie bee neuer ſo great for the preſent, yet it is inconſtant, &amp; ſhall not indure.<note place="margin">Pſalme 73.18</note> The Lord <hi>ſetts them in ſlipperie places, &amp; caſteth them down into deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp; ſodainly are they deſtroyed, peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and horribly conſumed.</hi> For euen in the midſt of their wealth, they are but fatted &amp; <hi>prepared for the day of ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ierem. 12.3</note> And thus much ſhall ſuffiſe for the firſt point, which I haue the lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted on, becauſe it is ſo neceſſary for vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is good that I was afflicted.)</hi> This muſt be vnderſtood of croſſes that are ſanctified, when GOD giueth grace to make an holie vſe of them. It is true, affliction in it owne nature, is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, and a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ag of Gods vengeance, &amp; a puniſhment for ſin. But, as the bitter waters,<note place="margin">Exod. 15.25</note> which the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> complay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of in the wilderneſſe, were made
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:20488:39"/>
ſweet by a tree, which <hi>Moſes</hi> by Gods direction caſt into them: ſo the Croſſe of <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath ſeaſoned and ſweetened all afflictions to the children of God, which haue grace to profite by them: ſo that now the nature of them is chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and altered, that they are no more a puniſhment of ſinne, but a medicine for the ſinner. According to that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent ſpeech of <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Non poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, ſed reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentium. Pſal. 94.12.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed is the man whom thou chaſteneſt, O Lord, and teacheſt him in thy Law.</hi> If the Lord do ioyne his teaching to his correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to cauſe a man wiſely to make vſe thereof, it is a moſt happy and bleſſed condition. Wherevnto agreeth that ſaying of the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12.11:</note> 
               <hi>No chaſtiſing for the preſent ſeemeth to bee ioyous, but grieuous: but afterwardes it bringeth with it the quiet fruit of righteouſneſſe, vnto them which are thereby exerciſed.</hi> If a man be truely exerciſed with af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, hee ſhall finde great fruit and benefite by it. So then heere wee are taught, that afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is very profitable and good for the children of God. That God, who by his mighty power
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:20488:39"/>
               <hi>commaunded the light to ſhine out of darkeneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.6</note> hath ſo ordered the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in his heauenly wiſedome, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen thoſe things, which to mans na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and to fleſh and bloud, are moſt irkeſome and weariſome, ſhould bee to his children moſt beneficiall and wholeſome. For (as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith) <hi>All things worke together for the beſt vnto them that loue God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.28</note> In that hee ſaith, <hi>all things,</hi> hee excepteth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. Not onely proſperity but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſity alſo, not onely good ſucceſſe, but loſſes and caſualties: not health onely but ſickenes: not life but death alſo, make for the good of thoſe that be godly. And indeed, affliction doth not only miniſter comfort vnto them, in that, as we haue heard, it is a pledge of their adoption, but it produceth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo many bleſſed and gracious effects.</p>
            <p>Firſt of all, it is a means to purge out the droſſe of that naturall corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that is within vs. So long as wee enioy proſperity, it is with vs as the Prophet ſaith of <hi>Moab,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ierem 48.11 Zephan. 1.12</note> wee are like Wine that <hi>is ſetled on his lees, and fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:20488:40"/>
in his dregges, and hath not beene powred out from veſſell to veſſell.</hi> So wee are full of the dregges of naturall cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, till the Lord by affliction doe refine vs. Affliction (as one ſaith well) is vnto the children of God, as the flaile is to the corne, the file to the yron, and the fire to the golde:<note n="a" place="margin">Si aurum es, per ignem purgaris<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſi ferrum es, ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biginem a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittis.</note> As the flaile doth purge the corne from the chaffe, which groweth vp with it: and as the file ſcowreth off the ruſt that ſticketh vpon the yron: and as the fire purifieth the gold from the droſſe: So doth affliction, by Gods mercie, purge away from vs that chaffe, that ruſt, and droſſe of ſinne, that is in our nature. The Gold-ſmith taketh not the golde out of the forge, till hee ſee it well and throughly purified. In like manner, God doth not remooue the afflictions of his children, till they be throughly refined. In a word, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction is the Lordes pruning knife, whereby he cutteth away from vs all withered and vnprofitable branches.</p>
            <p>Secondly, affliction that is ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, doth bring a man to the ſight of
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:20488:40"/>
his ſinnes, and to godly ſorrow, and true repentance for the ſame.<note n="a" place="margin">Oculos quos culpa claudit, poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na aperit. Greg. in Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral.</note> As ſinne ſhutteth vp a mans eyes, ſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction openeth them. And heereof we haue a worthy example in the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of <hi>Ioſeph.</hi> For the ſpace of twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie yeares they were neuer touched with any remorſe, for their vnnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall cruelty, in ſelling of him to the <hi>Iſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maelites:</hi> till at the laſt, comming into <hi>Aegypt,</hi> to buy corne, in the time of the famine: and perceiuing <hi>Ioſeph</hi> to ſpeake roughly to them, and to charge them to be Spies, that came to ſee the weakeneſſe of the Land: and fearing impriſonment, or ſome other hard meaſure, then they beganne to call their ſinne to remembrance, and to ſay one to another, <hi>Wee haue ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely ſinned againſt our brother, in that wee ſawe the anguiſh of his ſoule when he beſought vs, and we would not heare him: therefore is this trouble come vpon vs. Geneſis</hi> 42.21. As one that is faſt aſleepe, will not awake vnleſſe hee be raiſed by thruſting, or by ſome ſuch violent motion: ſo many lie
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:20488:41"/>
ſnorting in the long cuſtome of ſinne, and neuer thinke of repentance, till the hand of God be vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And as the <hi>horſe that ruſheth into the battell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ierem. 8.6.</note> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther feareth the enemy that commeth againſt him, nor is terrified with the dolefull groanes of dying perſons, nor with the noyſe of the gunnes, nor with the ſhaking of the pikes: ſo wicked men are carried headlong to ſinne, and neither feare the roaring of the diuell, nor are moued with the miſerable end of others before their eyes, nor terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with the feare of hell. But as the horſe running with violence, being checked by his rider with a ſharpe bridle, is enforced to ſtay his courſe. So, when ſinners runne into all exceſſe of riot, the Lord in mercie, by one affliction or other, as it were by ſtrong hand, pulleth them backe, and cauſeth them to ſee their ſinnes, and ſo brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth them to repentance. So that wee ſee that God vſeth his corrections as Sermons, to call his children from their ſinnes, which many times are more forcible and effectuall then any
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:20488:41"/>
verball preaching. According to that ſaying of <hi>S. Auguſtine,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Multi cum ſentiunt poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam, corri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunt culpam, in Pſal. 50:</note> Many men when they feele the ſmart, reforme the falt. Now what greater benefite can there be then this for a man to be brought to vnfained repentance for his ſins, without which there can be no hope of forgiuenes. And therefore <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith ſweetely.<note n="b" place="margin">Bene pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geris, fi com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pungeris, in Pſal. 32.</note> It is a good affliction, that bringeth a man to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punction, and remorſe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, affliction is as a notable meanes to humble the children of God, and to beate downe their pride. So long as all things goe well with vs, and we are free from the croſſe, our fleſh is puffed vp, and can hardly be kept vnder, the leven of old <hi>Adam</hi> is in vs, and maketh vs ſwell in pride. As the moone neuer ſuffereth eclipſe, but when ſhe is in the full, and then ſhe is alwayes furtheſt diſtant from the ſun: ſo likewiſe when we abound in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward proſperitie, ſuch is the fooliſh pride of our hearts, we are puffed vp, and care leaſt for God, till by ſome af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction or other he humble vs and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:20488:42"/>
bring vs downe. Thus was it with the <hi>Prodigall ſon.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lu, 15.17. etc.</note> As ſoone as hee had got his portion of his father, he was all on flaunt, &amp; knew not himſelfe, hee could ſtand on no ground: but when he had waſted his ſubſtance, and was pinched with pouerty and famine, his pride was danted, &amp; hee was glad to come home by weeping croſſe.<note place="margin">Gen. 16.4, 9</note> So was it with <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar</hi> when ſhe had conceiued a child by her maſter <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſhe was preſently ſo lifted vp with pride, that ſhe deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed her miſtris <hi>Sara,</hi> becauſe ſhee was barren. But afterwards, when her mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris had dealt roughly with her, and made her run away into the wildernes, ſhe cried <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ccaui,</hi> and humbled herſelfe vnder her hands. Yea <hi>Dauid</hi> himſelfe, though otherwiſe an holy man, had a ſpice of this diſeaſe, as himſelfe confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth,<note place="margin">Pſal. 30.6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>In my proſperitie</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I ſaid I ſhall neuer be mooued. For thou Lord of thy goodnes hadſt made my mountaine to ſtand ſtrong.</hi> See how ſoone a man is apt to forget himſelfe,<note place="margin">Preſſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruit, tumor exc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>euit, Aug. in Pſal. 51.</note> if hee enioy but alittle proſperitie. But alas, the caſe was ſoone altered with him. For as he
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:20488:42"/>
ſaith in the next words, <hi>The Lord did but hide his face,</hi> and bring him into ſome affliction, and ſtraitway hee <hi>was troubled.</hi> And therefore, in this reſpect affliction is very neceſſary and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, becauſe it cauſeth a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to know himſelfe. As we ſee by common expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, when God afflicteth a man ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with ignominy and diſgrace in his name, or with pouerty in his eſtate, or with ſickenes in his body, or with loſſe of children, or any ſuch like croſſe and calamity, though before hee were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo prowd, and carried himſelfe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo high, yet then he beginneth to droope, and letteth his feathers fall.<note n="a" place="margin">Plut in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheg. Reg: et Imp.</note> 
               <hi>Antigonus,</hi> though an heathen king, when he was taken with alittle ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and had recouered thereof, he could make this good conſtruction of it, namely, that it was well for him that hee had beene ſicke and ill: for his diſeaſe had taught him, that ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hee was but a mortall man, hee ſhould not too much lift vppe his Spirite. And this is the goodneſſe of God towards vs, as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:20488:43"/>
ſaith,<note n="a" place="margin">Auguſt. de vera Relig.</note> That becauſe the ſweetneſſe of earthly bleſsings doth deceiue vs and puffe vs vp, we ſhould be humbled by the bitternes of affliction.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, affliction is a meanes to reforme the godly, and to make them better: That which <hi>Salomon</hi> ſpeaketh of children, is true alſo of aged per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,<note place="margin">Prou. 22.15</note> that <hi>follie is bound in their hearts, but the rodde of correction ſhall driue it away from them.</hi> And therefore, the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith well. That when GOD correcteth &amp; chaſteneth his children, it is but to <hi>Nurture</hi> them (as a louing father doth his ſonne) for their refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation and amendment.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11:32</note> 
               <hi>When we are iudged,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>we are nurtered of the Lord, &amp;c.</hi> The Lord knoweth, that a ſonne ſet at libertie, runneth into ſuch licentious courſes, that he is a ſhame to his father, and a griefe to his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and therefore hee will not ſuffer his children whom hee loueth moſt tenderly, to goe on in their ſinnes, leſt his name ſhould be diſhonoured, and his holy Goſpel euill ſpoken of, but by corrections and croſſes laboureth to
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:20488:43"/>
reclaime them. As <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Iob 33.16, 17</note> 
               <hi>Hee ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the eares of men, euen by their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections which he hath ſealed: That hee might cauſe man to turne away from his enterpriſe, &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>Solomon</hi> hath a ſpeech to the ſame purpoſe,<note place="margin">Prou. 6.23.</note> that <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections for inſtruction are the way of life,</hi> to keepe and preſerue a man from whooredome, and ſuch like ſinnes:<note n="a" place="margin">Felix neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitas quae co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git in melius. De praecepto et diſpenſat.</note> So that this (as <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith) muſt needes be a happy and bleſſed afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that maketh a man better.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, affliction is an excellent means to inforce vs, and ſtirre vs vp to pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. Yea, euen they that neuer thought to pray, as <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> and wicked per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, when any trouble lyeth vpon them, are driuen to pray whether they will or no. As the <hi>Prophet</hi> ſaith, That ſuch as rebell againſt God, in the time of famine, when they want corne and wine, <hi>will howle vpon their beds.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſea 7.14</note> And <hi>Dauid</hi> reckoneth vp a bead-roll of ſuch perſons.<note place="margin">Pſal. 107.4, 5</note> Some that <hi>wandered out of the way in the wildernes, and found no citty to dwell in, both hungry &amp; thirſty, their ſoule fainting in them.</hi> Others that
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:20488:44"/>
               <hi>dwell in darkeneſſe and in the ſhadow of death:</hi>
               <note place="margin">10.</note> that is, poore priſoners, <hi>being bound in miſery and yron.</hi> Others being caſt on their ſicke beds,<note place="margin">18.</note> 
               <hi>whoſe ſoule ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horreth all maner of meate, and they are brought to deaths doore.</hi> Others in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of ſhipwracke,<note place="margin">26:</note> 
               <hi>whoſe ſoule meltsth for trouble, &amp;c.</hi> Howſoeuer peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in the time of their proſperity, they cared but alittle for the Lord, yet now they <hi>cryed to him in their trouble,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe 6.13, 19, 28</note> 
               <hi>&amp; he deliuered them out of their diſtreſſe:</hi> So that trouble and diſtreſſe will make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man cry vnto the Lord, and betake him to his prayers. So was it with the mariners that entertained <hi>Ionah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ionah 1.5</note> when they were afraid of their liues, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the mightie tempeſt that God ſent vpon them, they <hi>cried euery man to his God.</hi> And the prowd king of <hi>Nineueh,</hi> with all his people, when they heard the ſodaine deſtruction that was threatned againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of <hi>Ionah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">and 3.8 2 Chro. 33.6</note> they <hi>cried mightily vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God.</hi> And that wicked <hi>Manaſſeh, who did very much euill in the ſight of the Lord to anger him:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Kin. 21.16.</note> 
               <hi>ſhedding inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:20488:44"/>
bloud exceeding much, till hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleniſhed Ieruſalem from corner to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner:</hi> yet when God brought vpon him the Captaines of the King of <hi>Aſhur,</hi> which tooke him, and put him in fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and bound him in chaines, and carried him to <hi>Babel, then when he was in tribulation, he prayed to the Lord his God, and humbled himſelfe greatly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the God of his fathers.</hi> Yea the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly themſelues are neuer ſo fit to pray, as when they are in affliction. Though they be carefull to pray continually:<note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5.17.</note> yet they neuer pray with ſo great deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and feruencie, as when ſome heauy croſſe or calamity is vpon them. For then feeling their miſerie, and their owne inabilitie to helpe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, they more earneſtly flie vnto the Lord for ſuccour. As the <hi>Prophet</hi> ſaith, <hi>In that day,</hi> that is,<note place="margin">Eſay 17.7.</note> in the day of trouble, <hi>ſhall a man looke to his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, and his eyes ſhall looke to the holy one of Iſrael.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſea 5.15.</note> And <hi>in their affliction they wil ſeek me diligently,</hi> ſaith the Lord. In our proſperity wee are all of vs both good &amp; bad, too full of ſecurity, as thogh we
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:20488:45"/>
ſtood no neede of God. As the Lord complaineth of <hi>Ieconiah</hi> ſaying,<note place="margin">Ierem. 22.21</note> 
               <hi>I ſpake to thee when thou waſt in proſperity: but thou ſaidſt, I will not heare &amp;c.</hi> And ſo <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith of the wicked that becauſe <hi>his wayes alway proſper,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalm 10.4, 5</note> 
               <hi>and the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God are high aboue his ſight:</hi> therefore he is ſo prowd, that <hi>hee ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſeeketh after God.</hi> And the <hi>Prophet Ieremiah</hi> compareth ſuch perſons to the <hi>wilde Aſſe in the wilderneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ierem. 2.24</note> 
               <hi>that ſnuffeth vp the winde at her pleaſure: and it is in vaine to ſeeke to turne her backe, but in her moneth,</hi> that is, in her foaling time, then a man may deale with her. As the little Chickens, when the weather is faire, and there is no dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger towardes, ſtraggle a great waie from the Henne: but if any Hayle ſhewer come vpon them, or a Kite houer ouer them, then they are glad to runne vnder her wings for ſhelter. And as the Stagge, when he is at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, will not come neare a man: but when hee is hotly purſued with the dogges, hee will runne to him of his owne accord for ſuccour: So it fareth
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:20488:45"/>
oftentimes with vs, when wee are at eaſe, and nothing doth moleſt vs, wee turne our backes vpon GOD: but when wee are brought into diſtreſſe or danger, we are glad to repaire vnto him for helpe. As one confeſſeth of himſelfe (and it is our caſe aſwell as his)<note n="a" place="margin">Si bene eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſem ſine te, non venitem ad te.</note> If I could be well without thee, I would neuer come at thee. As the water when it is at large, and hath ſcope enough, runneth with a ſtill and ſilent motion, but being brought into a ſtreight, it maketh a great noyſe: In like manner, when a man is at large, he looketh not much to this duetie of prayer: but when hee is in affliction and ſtraites, hee will excite and ſtirre vp himſelfe thereunto. So did the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in the time of their bondage, they <hi>ſighed, and cryed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exo. 2:23, 24</note> 
               <hi>and made their moane vnto GOD.</hi> And wee reade in many places of the Booke of <hi>Iudges,</hi> That howſoeuer in their proſperity they were vntoward &amp; careleſſe of God,<note place="margin">Chap. 3. and 4</note> yet when God raiſed vp any new enemies againſt them, they cryed vnto him. And <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:20488:46"/>
of himſelfe, that although before, while he thought his mountain to be ſtrong enough (as we haue heard) he was foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh and prowd: yet when God hid his face from him,<note place="margin">Pſal. 30.2</note> then hee <hi>cryed vnto the Lord and praied vnto him.</hi> And we may obſcrue, that the moſt of his <hi>Pſalmes</hi> were made when hee was in affliction. Yea our <hi>Sauior Chriſt</hi> himſelfe, thogh all his lifetime hee was much conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant in prayer, ſometime riſing earely in the morning before day,<note place="margin">Mar. 1.35</note> and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time ſpending the whole night there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: yet he neuer prayed more earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, nor more feruently, then immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately before his paſsion: when, as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Heb. 5.7</note> 
               <hi>he offered vp prayers and ſupplications with ſtrong crying and teares:</hi> yea he was ſo ſeruent, that <hi>his ſweat was like droppes of bloud trickling downe to the ground.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 22.44</note> Wee ſee then by all that hath beene ſpoken, that affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is as it were a whet-ſtone, to ſet an edge vpon our deuotion, and ſhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen our hearts to prayer.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, affliction doth containe the children of God in obedience. It is
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:20488:46"/>
with the beſt of vs, as <hi>Agiſelaus</hi> ſaid of the <hi>Athenians;</hi> that<note n="a" place="margin">Liberi ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unt, ſerui boni.</note> When they were at libertie they were nought, but when they were in bondage, they were good: ſo we in our proſperity do ſtart aſide like a broken bow, but when af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction commeth, wee ſubmitte our ſelues to the Lords yoke. The people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when the hand of God was vpon them, eyther by warre, or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, or any other calamity, carried themſelues very religiouſly, and wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in obedience vnto his will. But when God <hi>carryed them vp to the high places of the earth</hi> (as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaith) <hi>that they might eate the fruites of the fieldes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 32.i3, 14, 15</note> 
               <hi>when hee cauſed them to ſucke hony out of the ſtone, &amp; oile out of the hard rocke: when hee gaue them butter of kine, and milke of ſheepe, with fatte of lambes and rammes fed in Baſhan, with the fatte of the graines of wheate: and made them drinke the red liquor of the grape: then they that ſhould haue beene vpright, when they waxed fatte, ſpurned with their heeles: they were fat, they were groſſe, they were laden with fatneſſe:
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:20488:47"/>
therefore they forſooke God that made them, and regarded not the ſtrong God of their ſaluation.</hi> And this doth <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> confeſſe of himſelfe, when he ſaith, <hi>Before I was afflicted I went aſtray,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.67</note> 
               <hi>but now I keep thy word.</hi> And the Church acknowledgeth, that before the <hi>Lord corrected her,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ierem: 31.18</note> 
               <hi>ſhee was like an vntamed calfe.</hi> Though man were created after the Image of God, and aduaunced to great honour, yet if God let him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone,<note place="margin">Pſal. 49.20</note> hee will become like vnto <hi>the beaſts that periſh,</hi> as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith. And therefore, the Lord threatneth the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious <hi>Iewes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſea 2.6</note> that <hi>he will ſtoppe their way with thornes, and make an hedge, that they ſhould not finde their pathes.</hi> Where hee ſheweth that neceſsitie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth, that hee ſhould holde them in with ſeuere Diſcipline and ſharpe corrections, comparing them to wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton and vnruly cattell, which muſt bee kept in with thornes and hedges, leſt they leape out of the paſture, and goe aſtray.</p>
            <p>Seauenthly, it helpeth to tame and ſubdue the vnrulineſſe of the fleſh, that
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:20488:47"/>
it may be in better ſubiection to the Spirit. The fleſh is like an head-ſtrong horſe, which if he be fatted and pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered in the ſtable for a while, waxeth ſo frampall, as hee can hardly be ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and brought to acknowledge his rider: So this ſtubborne fleſh of ours, if it inioy but alitle proſperity, it ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way groweth ſo rebellious, that it will not be <hi>ſubiect to the Law of God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.7</note> And as the horſe-rider, to pull downe the ſtomacke of ſuch an horſe, taketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his prouender, and feedeth him with ſtraw and chaffe: and if that will not ſerue, handleth him roughly, and beateth him. So doth the Lord with our fleſh: hee taketh away thoſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward bleſsings which puffed it vp, and made it ſwell, and loadeth it with one affliction after another,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.27</note> that ſo he <hi>may beate it downe and bring it into ſubiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> And this is a great benefite, to haue the fleſh, with the curſed luſtes and affections thereof, mortified and ſubdued in this maner. For it is one of thoſe deadly enemies of our ſoules,<note place="margin">Galat. 5.17</note> with which we muſt fight and incoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:20488:48"/>
while we liue. Now as he that were to enter a ſingle combate, with an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſary that were ſtronger then him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, would be glad of ſome bodie would firſt weaken and foyle him, that ſo he might the more eaſily ouercome him: In like manner, the children of God haue cauſe to reioyce, that it doth pleaſe the Lord by outward calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to tame the fleſh, and to treade it vnder their feete, that ſo they may with leſſe difficulty and danger get the mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of it.</p>
            <p>Eightly, it is a meanes to withdraw our hearts from the loue of the world, &amp; to raiſe them vp to the deſire of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly things. Such is the corruption of our nature, that we doate too much on this world. We are like to fooliſh chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, that would not willingly be wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from the breaſt, and therfore their mother annoynteth the nibbles of her breaſt with ſome bitter thing, to make them out of loue with it. So, if wee might haue our wills, wee would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes hang vpon the breaſts of the world, &amp; would neuer leaue ſucking,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:20488:48"/>
if the Lord did not powder our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires with the croſſe, and make them bitter to vs. The children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> though they were grieuouſly afflicted in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> to make them more ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly deſire to poſſeſſe the land of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan:</hi> yet we ſee how hardly they were brought to depart from thence. Yea, when they were in the way to <hi>Canaan,</hi> they would often haue returned backe againe into <hi>Aegypt</hi> to their <hi>fleſh-pots,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num i4.3, 4 Exod. 16.3 Num. 11.5</note> 
               <hi>their fiſh, their cucumbers, their pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, &amp;c.</hi> If they had liued in preferre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment there, and enioyed the fatte of the land, as they did in <hi>Ioſephs</hi> time,<note place="margin">Gen. 45.18 and 47.11</note> it would, no doubt, haue beene an hard matter to haue perſwaded them to depart. So it fareth with the moſt of vs: wee are in this world, as in a Sea of miſery, neuer out of one danger or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, yet ſuch is our folly, we loue to be here ſtill. What would we do if we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer had any thing to moleſt vs? It is a lamentable thing to conſider that our mindes ſhould bee ſo dazeled with the glittring ſhew of riches, pleſures &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, as they cannot look to heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:20488:49"/>
our hearts ſhould be ſo oppreſſed and weighed downe with couetouſnes and ambition, that they can not raiſe vp themſelues vnto celeſtiall cogitations, and that our ſoules ſhould be ſo enſna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the pleaſant inticements of the fleſh, that they ſeeke for their felicitie vpon the earth. And therfore the Lord in mercy to preuent this euill, doth by daily experience of miſeries, put his children in minde of the vanity of all earthly things,<note place="margin">Caluin. inſtit. lib. 3. cap 9. ſect. 1.</note> leſt they ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to themſelues a conſtant and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall peace in this world, hee ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth them many times to bee diſquie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and moleſted, with warres, with tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults, with robberies, and other iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: leſt they ſhould with too much greedines gape after brittle and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant riches, or ſhould too much reſt in thoſe which they doe poſſeſſe, God bringeth them to pouerty, ſometimes by baniſhment, ſometimes by barren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the earth, ſometimes by fire, ſometimes by one meanes, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by another, leſt they ſhould take too much delight in the comfortes of
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:20488:49"/>
marriage, he eyther cauſeth them to be vexed with the ſhrewdneſſe of their wiues, or humbleth them with lewd children, or afflicteth them with the loſſe and death of their children. And if it fall out that the Lord doe ſpare them in all theſe things: yet, leſt they ſhould either ſwell with vaine-glorie, or reioyce with fooliſh confidence, he chaſteneth them with ſickeneſſe and diſeaſes, that they may learne how fraile and vnſtable all earthly things are, and may lift vp their eyes to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, where that incorruptible crowne of glory is laid vp for them. And thus the Lord in his vnſpeakeable good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes many times diminiſheth the health of our bodies, that we may more ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly deſire the ſaluation of our ſouls. He taketh away the things of this life, that we may more carefully ſeeke after the things of a better life. So that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions are like to a great ſtorme at Sea,<note place="margin">Philip. 1.23</note> to make the godly wiſh to be in the hauen. As the waters of the deluge, the more they increaſed, the higher they bare vp the Arke: So the waters
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:20488:50"/>
of tribulation, the greater they are, the higher they lift vp the ſoule towardes heauen: according to that ſpeech of <hi>Bernard,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Per flagella domini ſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuntur te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, amantur coeleſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a. De coena dom. ſerm 10</note> By the Lords corrections we contemne earthly things, and loue heauenly. And therefore, as <hi>Zeno</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Diog. La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ertius in vita Zenonis.</note> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſuffered ſhipwracke, became the Scholler of <hi>Crates,</hi> and ſtudied <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophie,</hi> and after ſaid it was an happie ſhipwracke that made him affect ſuch excellent knowledge: So may wee ſay much more truly It was a bleſſed ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, a bleſſed pouerty, a bleſſed impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment &amp;c, that cauſed vs to looke towardes the kingdome of heauen.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, affliction doeth ſaue the children of God from hell &amp; condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. If God ſhould let vs alone, we would neuer reſt till we run headlong to hell: as fooliſh childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if they be not hinderd, will run into the ditch. And therefore, it is the Lords mercie, to lay the rodde vpon our backs, that ſo we may bethinke our ſelues of the danger wherein wee ſtand, and may labour to preuent it. And this is that which <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Iob 33 16.18</note> that the Lord <hi>openeth the eares of
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:20488:50"/>
men by corrections,</hi> that ſo he may <hi>keepe backe their ſoules from the pit, and that their life ſhould not paſſe by the ſword.</hi> And the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> hath a ſaying to the ſame purpoſe,<note place="margin">i Cor. 11.32.</note> that <hi>when we are iudged we are chaſtened of the Lord becauſe we ſhould not be condemned with the world</hi> When a man is deſperately about to caſt himſelfe into the fire, or to drowne himſelfe in the water, can any do him a greater benefite then to preuent him and ſaue his life? So there cannot be a greater benefit to vs, then when we are ready to drowne our ſelues in perditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by our ſinnes, that the Lord by his corrections ſhould ſtay vs, and holde vs backe.</p>
            <p>Laſt of all, affliction doth fitte and prepare vs for the kingdome of Heauen. As the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith of the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> that <hi>by perſecutions and tribulations which they ſuffered, they were counted woorthie of the kingdome of God.</hi> 2. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.5 As the parching heat of the Sun ripeneth the corne, and maketh it fitte to bee carried into the barn: ſo doth afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ripen the godly,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:20488:51"/>
that they may be meet to be gathered into Gods barne. And this is done two wayes: Firſt, becauſe by afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as wee haue heard<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wee are pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and purified from our ſins, which elſe would hinder vs from comming there.<note place="margin">Apocal. 21.27</note> For <hi>no vncleane thing ſhall enter into Gods kingdome.</hi> As gold muſt firſt be purified in the fire, before it be laid vp in the kings treaſury:<note place="margin">Prou. 25.4</note> &amp; as wheat muſt be cleanſed from the chaffe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it be laid vp in the garner: ſo muſt it be with vs. Affliction is the fire that muſt purge vs,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.21.</note> to make vs <hi>veſſels of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> for the houſe of God: and the fan that muſt clenſe vs, to make vs pure wheat for his garner. In the building of <hi>Solomons</hi> temple,<note place="margin">1 Kings 6.7</note> all the ſtones were hewen and fitted in the quarry, before they were brought thither: and <hi>There was neither hammer, nor axe, nor anie toole of yron heard in the temple while it was in building.</hi> So in the kingdome of heauen, which is the ſpirituall houſe of God, all <hi>the liuing ſtones</hi> thereof, muſt be hewen, and ſquared, and fitted by afflictions in this life. Secondly,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:20488:51"/>
affliction prepareth vs for heauen, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is a meanes to worke holines in vs,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.14</note> 
               <hi>without which no man ſhall euer ſee the Lord,</hi> as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith. We ſee then by all theſe gracious effects and bleſſed fruits which affl ction brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth with it, that <hi>Dauid</hi> had good cauſe to ſay, <hi>It is good for mee that I haue beene afflicted.</hi> And therefore wee may conclude with Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Percutis, vt ſanes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidis nos, ne moriamur abs te. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onfeſt. lib. 2.</note> The Lord ſmiteth vs that hee may heale vs, and killeth vs that wee may not die from him.</p>
            <p>This Doctrine (that wee may make <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> ſome vſe of it) doth teach vs, firſt of all, to labour to perſwade our ſelues of this great and excellent good that affliction bringeth with it, that ſo we may <hi>count it exceeding ioy when we fall into it.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iames 1.2</note> I confeſſe it ſeemeth other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to fleſh and bloud. For,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.11.</note> as the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle</hi> ſaith truely, <hi>no chaſtiſing for the preſent ſeemeth to be ioyous, but grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous.</hi> As children are loath to feele the ſmart of the rodde, nay, they can not indure to heare of it; ſo is our corrupt nature loath and vnwilling to taſte of
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:20488:52"/>
any correctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. It is death to vs, to hear that we muſt be <hi>puniſhed &amp; chaſtened e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery morning:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalme 73.14</note> and that we muſt be <hi>fed with the bread of tears,</hi>
               <note place="margin">and 10.5.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; haue tears to drinke in great meaſure.</hi> It is a wearie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome thing to be alwayes ſicke &amp; lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing,<note place="margin">and 107.18.</note> ſo as <hi>the ſoule abhorreth all maner of meate:</hi> to be continually full of cramps &amp; aches and pains, ſo as nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a mans <hi>couch can relieue him, nor his bed bring comfort vnto him,</hi> as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith.<note place="margin">Iob 7.i3:</note> But when he <hi>layeth him downe, he ſaith, when ſhall I riſe, and the night bee gone?</hi> and, <hi>he is full with toſsing to and fro vnto the dawning of the day.</hi>
               <note place="margin">4.</note> The like may be ſaid of all other afflictions, they are as vnſauoury to the fleſh, as <hi>the white of an egge without ſalt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 6.6.</note> And therefore our <hi>Sauiour Chriſt</hi> himſelfe, as he was man,<note place="margin">Heb. 2 14.</note> and ſo partaker of our infirmities, felt in his fleſh a loathneſſe to haue taſted of that bitter cup of his Paſsion,<note place="margin">Matt. 26.38 39.</note> 
               <hi>his ſoule was heauie vnto the death,</hi> and therefore hee beſought his Father, that <hi>if it were poſsible it might paſſe from him:</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Ser in f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ia, 5. in Paraſc.</note> which ſpeech, as <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> noteth, ſeemeth to be the ſpeech
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:20488:52"/>
of the fleſh, &amp; not of the ſpirit, becauſe he addeth alittle after, <hi>the ſpirit is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, but the fleſh is weake.</hi> But we muſt not meaſure afflictions by the preſent ſmart we feele in them, but by the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit that follows after them. For as we haue heard, thogh the ſenſe of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent griefe be bitter, yet the fruit that commeth after is moſt ſweet and plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſant. Affliction is to the ſoule, as <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke</hi> to the body. But as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly that <hi>Phyſicke</hi> which is moſt wholeſome, is withall moſt vntoothſome: ſo that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction which is moſt profitable, is for the moſt part moſt diſtaſtefull. As the plant which they call <hi>Chriſts thorne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plin. lib, 24. cap. 14.</note> is extreme bitter both in the root and in the leaues, &amp; in the branches; but yet is very medicinable (for the iuyce of the root cleareth the eyes, the ſeede brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth downe the after-birth, &amp;c.) So affliction, though it be in it ſelfe moſt bitter and vnſauoury, yet the Lord our moſt skilfull <hi>Phyſition,</hi> maketh moſt ſoueraigne medicines thereof,<note place="margin">Pſal. 103.3.</note> to <hi>heale the infirmities</hi> of his children, whereby it becommeth more profitable to them
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:20488:53"/>
then (by reaſon of their corruption) proſperitie could euer be. For as dead fleſh, if it be kept in ſweete water, will corrupt and be full of wormes: but if it be kept in ſalt brine, it will be preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued long, and become wholeſome meate for the vſe of man: ſo the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, if they abound with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity, are eaſily corrupted, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing exerciſed by the croſſe, they are preſerued from the infection of ſinne.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it teacheth vs to indeuour by all meanes; to profite by the affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions that God layeth vpon vs, that ſo we may haue experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of this good which they bring with them: that ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God intendeth them for our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite, ſo wee may not by our owne ſtubbornneſſe and vntowardnes, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert them to our hurt. It is as grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous a ſinne as we can commit, to har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den our hearts when Gods hand is vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs. As the Lord complained of the <hi>Iewes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ierem. 2.30.</note> 
               <hi>I haue ſmitten your children in vaine, they haue receiued no correction.</hi> And in an other place.<note place="margin">and 5.3.</note> 
               <hi>O Lord</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Prophet) Thou haſt ſtricken them,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:20488:53"/>
and they haue not ſorrowed: thou haſt conſumed them, but they haue refuſed to receiue correction: they haue made their faces harder then a ſtone, and haue refuſed to returne.</hi> And ſo it is ſaid of <hi>Ahaz,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chr. 28.22.</note> that <hi>in the time of his tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hee did treſpaſſe more againſt the Lord.</hi> Let vs therfore bleſſe our ſelues from this height of iniquitie, and let vs pray to God, to ſanctifie all our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections and chaſticements vnto vs, that wee may bee bettered and refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by them: So ſhall they be infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble arguments of his fatherly loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vs: otherwiſe they will be fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full tokens of his wrath, and certaine pledges of our condemnation.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it teacheth vs to be pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> vnder the croſſe: For as the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.9.</note> 
               <hi>If we haue had the fathers of our bodies which corrected vs, we gaue them reuerence: ſhould we not much ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be in ſubiection vnto the Father of Spirites, that wee may liue?</hi> eſpecially conſidering that it is ſo much for our good. A man that is ſicke of a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning feuer, willingly ſuffereth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:20488:54"/>
to be let bloud, becauſe he kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth it is a meanes to abate the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of his diſeaſe. A man that is pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the ſtone, patiently yeeldeth himſelfe to be cut and tortured by the <hi>Phyſition,</hi> becauſe hee knoweth it is a means to preſerue his life. A man that is wounded, meekly ſuffereth the <hi>Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon</hi> to launch and ſearch his wound to the bottome, and with ſharpe cora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiues to eate out the feſtered core of the vlcer, becauſe hee knoweth he can not otherwiſe be cured. Shall all theſe endure, and that with admirable pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, ſo much torment for the good of their bodies, and ſhall not wee much more be willing, to ſuffer Gods ſhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt corrections for the benefite of our ſoules? eſpecially, ſeeing our owne ſinnes haue deſerued the greateſt puniſhments that GOD can in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict.<note place="margin">Micah 7.9.</note> As the <hi>Prophet</hi> ſaith, <hi>I wil beare the wrath of the Lord, becauſe I haue ſinned againſt him.</hi> And therefore, let vs learne meekely and obediently to ſubmitte our ſelues to the will of God in this caſe. And as hee ſendeth affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:20488:54"/>
with a right hand, let vs not take them with a left. An olde Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier that had ſerued <hi>Caligula, Claudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> and <hi>Nero,</hi> three cruell tyrants, Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours of <hi>Rome,</hi> being demaunded how he could eſcape the dangers of thoſe times, wherein ſo many worthie Cittizens were put to death. Hee an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerd: Euen by taking benefits thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and by putting vp iniuries pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently. If hee could for his owne ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſubdue his minde, to beare with patience the open iniuries of ſuch monſtrous tyrants: how much more ſhould wee ſubmitte our ſelues with all meekneſſe to beare the louing cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections of our moſt merciful Father? And howſoeuer it may ſeeme, that God layeth heauier and ſorer afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons vpon vs, then vpon many others: yet wee muſt conſider, that hee kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth the corruption and hardneſſe of our hearts to bee ſuch as could not bee ſubdewed with lighter corrections.<note n="a" place="margin">Malo nodo m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lus cuneus.</note> An hard knot, as the prouerb is, muſt haue an hard wedge. The <hi>Phyſition</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his potions milder or ſtronger,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:20488:55"/>
as the quality of the ſickeneſſe doth require. In like maner the Lord tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereth his corrections according to our diſpoſition: if he ſee vs tractable, he dealeth more gently with vs: if we be vntamed and rebellious, hee layeth it on, and maketh vs feele the ſmart. Neyther will hee euer ceaſe to follow vs with one calamity after an other, till hee haue brought vs to our knees, and cauſed vs to humble our ſelues ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently vnder his hand.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That I may learne thy ſtatutes.)</hi> Here the <hi>Prophet</hi> doth particularly declare that which before hee had generally propounded. Where by <hi>Learning</hi> hee doth not vnderſtand that contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue and ſpeculatiue learning which ſwimmeth in the braine, and is gotten by hearing and reading of the word of God: but that particular learning, which is gotten by experience. In a word, his meaning is this, that hee felt the truth and comfort of the word, more powerfull and effectuall in his afflictions, then at any time before, and that made him more carefull to
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:20488:55"/>
liue godly, when the croſſe was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued, and the trouble gone. From hence wee learne, that the godly doe feele the fruit of their afflictions, and are made better by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, when they are paſt and gone. They are not only good for the preſent, while they feele the ſmart, for ſo an hypocrite may ſeeme to be, but the benefite of their afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons remaineth with them all the daies of their liues. A proofe heereof wee haue in the example of <hi>Manaſſeh,</hi> who did not onely humble himſelfe great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly before the Lord, as wee haue heard before <hi>when he was in tribulation.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chron. 33</note> But when <hi>God was intreated of him,<note place="margin">12.</note> and heard his prayer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">13.</note> 
               <hi>and brought him again to Ieruſalem into his kingdome,</hi> then he reformed himſelfe from his wicked courſes, and reſtored the true worſhip of God. <hi>He tooke away the ſtrange gods,</hi>
               <note place="margin">.15.</note> 
               <hi>and the Image out of the houſe of the Lord, and all the Altars which himſelfe had built before, and caſt them out of the citty.</hi>
               <note place="margin">16.</note> 
               <hi>And he prepared the Altar of the Lord, and offered ſacrifice thereon, and commaunded Iudah to ſerue the Lord
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:20488:56"/>
God of Iſrael.</hi> The like wee ſee in that good king <hi>Hezekiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 38.3.</note> who was not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly religiouſly and deuoutly affected in the time of ſickneſſe, when he was paſt hope of life (for there is none ſo wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, but will make a ſhew of holineſſe then) but <hi>when hee was recouered of his ſickeneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">9. etc:</note> hee made a holy Song of thankeſgiuing, wherein hee profeſſeth the care that hee would haue of Gods ſeruice for the time to come: So that we ſee, the fruit of affliction endureth for euer vnto the children of God: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe they neuer made true vſe of it, they neuer reaped any profite by it. But I will not ſtand any longer in the proſecuting of this point.</p>
            <p>It ſerueth for the iuſt reproofe of all thoſe that make a ſhew to be ſomwhat good, in the time of trouble, but when it is gone, they are as badde as euer they were. So long as they feele the hand of GOD vpon them, they promiſe great reformation, but all is but hypocriſie. For they are no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner enlarged,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.22.</note> but they returne vnto their former courſes with as much
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:20488:56"/>
greedineſſe, as euer did the dog to his vomite. And herein they are like chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, who while the rodde is on their backs, promiſe great matters, that they will neuer do the like againe but they remember that promiſe no longer then they feele the ſmart of the rodde. And this wee ſee in the example of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> who ſo long as the plague was heauy vpon him &amp; his land, made no ſmall ſhew of repentance, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed; that if <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> would pray for him, that the plague might be remoued, hee would <hi>let the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple goe, they ſhould tarry no longer. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odus</hi> 9.27, 28. and 10 16, 17. But as ſoone as euer God had ſpared him at their intreaty, he was ſo farre from per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourming his promiſe, as his heart was more hardened, then euer it was before. Iron, whileſt it is in the fire, is ſoft, and pliable, and may be wroght into any forme: but if it bee taken from the fire alittle, it ſtraitway retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to his former hardneſſe. In like maner, many men, while they are in the furnace of afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſeem to haue ſoft &amp;
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:20488:57"/>
melting hearts, and make great ſhew of remorce for their ſinnes: but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, their hearts become as hard as the Adamant. And thus men doe vſe their repentance like an olde germent, they caſt it about them in a ſtorme or a ſhewer: but aſſoone as it is faire weather, they lay it by againe. But let vs bee carefull to make ſuch an holie and ſanctified vſe of our afflictions, when they be vpon vs, that wee may be the better for them all our life after. This point is neceſſary to be enlarged, but I haue handled it<note n="a" place="margin">In the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance of Peter and Iudas:</note> elſewhere, and therefore I will inſiſt no longer vpon it at this time.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
